<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Leaf</title>
  <subtitle>One in many, many in one.</subtitle>
  <id>https://serdars.github.io/</id>
  <link href="https://serdars.github.io/"/>
  <link href="https://serdars.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <updated>2014-12-29T11:03:00-08:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Serdar Sutay</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>Personal Mastery Poster</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://serdars.github.io/2014/12/29/personal-mastery-poster.html"/>
    <id>https://serdars.github.io/2014/12/29/personal-mastery-poster.html</id>
    <published>2014-12-29T11:03:00-08:00</published>
    <updated>2014-12-29T11:17:17-08:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Serdar Sutay</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Personal Mastery concept from &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peter_Senge"&gt;Peter M. Senge&lt;/a&gt; is a thing that we need to constantly keep in the back of our minds. Here is a poster that we can keep in our eye sight to remind us this concept.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Personal Mastery concept from &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peter_Senge"&gt;Peter M. Senge&lt;/a&gt; is a thing that we need to constantly keep in the back of our minds. Here is a poster that we can keep in our eye sight to remind us this concept.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img title="Personal Mastery Poster" class="full-width" src="/images/posters/personal-mastery.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can bookmark this poster in this address:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://serdars.github.io/images/posters/personal-mastery.png"&gt;https://serdars.github.io/images/posters/personal-mastery.png&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Peter M. Senge - The Fifth Discipline - Part 3 - Personal Mastery</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://serdars.github.io/2014/12/19/peter-m-senge-the-fifth-discipline-part-3-personal-mastery.html"/>
    <id>https://serdars.github.io/2014/12/19/peter-m-senge-the-fifth-discipline-part-3-personal-mastery.html</id>
    <published>2014-12-18T19:29:00-08:00</published>
    <updated>2014-12-29T10:57:24-08:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Serdar Sutay</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;One of the most important topics in &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peter_Senge"&gt;Peter M. Senge's&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/The-Fifth-Discipline-Practice-Organization/dp/0553456342"&gt;The Fifth Discipline&lt;/a&gt;: Personal Mastery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;One of the most important topics in &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peter_Senge"&gt;Peter M. Senge's&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/The-Fifth-Discipline-Practice-Organization/dp/0553456342"&gt;The Fifth Discipline&lt;/a&gt;: Personal Mastery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personal Mastery is the discipline of personal growth and learning. It is a generative activity. It covers the acquisition and development of competencies and skills but goes beyond it. It requires spiritual unfolding but it is more than that. At its core, it is composed of doing only two things:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Continuously clarifying what is important to us&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Clearly seeing current reality as it is&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sadly "mastery" word has bad connotations associated with it. In this context it doesn't suggest dominance over other things in life. A great example is John Petrucci. He is a great master but he doesn't dominate guitar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to continually clarify what is important to us, our personal vision, we need to learn more and more about ourselves. In order to learn more about ourselves we need to learn to be able to see the reality clearly. The clear we see the reality, we clear we can define what is really important for us. This is a reinforcing process based on learning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Learning in this sense doesn't mean acquiring more information. It is incorporating any information we acquire in our lives in order to expand our ability to produce results we would like to achieve. It is a never ending life long process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a person with high level of personal mastery:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Personal Vision is a calling rather than simply a good idea.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They see the current reality as an ally, not an enemy.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They work with the existing forces rather than resist them.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They feel part of a larger creative process that they can influence but can not unilaterally control.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why do we want personal mastery? As an organization, if the people working in the organization are committed to continuously improving themselves, this is in the interest of the organization. The happy people produce happy projects. As an individual we want it because we want it. Who doesn't want to achieve the thing they want most in life?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Organizations however sometimes resist personal mastery. Main reason is that, it is not easily quantifiable also sometimes due to cynicism. In order to fight cynicism, one needs to undestand the source of it. Most of the times it is due to a trauma one experienced. And lastly resistance comes from fear which is the primary blocker of learning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Approaching personal vision as a means to organization's goal devalues the relationship between the individual and the organization. Goal should be to create covenantal relationships rather than contractuals ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="personal-vision"&gt;Personal Vision&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personal Vision comes from within. Most of the times we have goals and objectives but no real vision. Most of the time goals point to things that we want to get rid of (aversion) in our lives. Let's use &lt;strong&gt;negative vision&lt;/strong&gt; as a term for these tendencies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another subtler form to watch out for is "focusing on the means not the result". This generally creates &lt;strong&gt;diminished vision&lt;/strong&gt;. Part of our vision is high market share. But why? In order to be more profitable. But why?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;The ability to focus on ultimate intrinsic desires, not only secondary goals, is a cornerstone of personal mastery.&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The vision can not be talked about without a purpose in life. Regardless of the ontological answer to this question, life's purpose is a useful concept to use. Purpose is similar to a direction, a general heading. Vision is a specific destination. Purpose is abstract. Vision is concrete. Vision without an underlying purpose is just a good idea. Purpose without a vision has no sense of appropriate scale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately vision is intrinsic, not relative. It is desired for its intrinsic value. It is multi-dimensional. There is material aspects, how much money we want to have; service facets, helping others; etc… All are part of what we truly want.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to develop a personal vision, one needs to approach it as a discipline and clear it constantly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a person with high level of personal mastery:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Is courageous enough to take a stand for his vision.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id="creative-tension"&gt;Creative Tension&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The gap between the current reality and the vision creates tension. Because we would like to resolve this gap. Not being able to resolve it quickly leads to two potential cases. If we're holding onto our vision strong enough it creates energy, a.k.a. creative tension, to pull us forward. If not, it creates emotional tension that pulls us back. Pretty much all the times we experience both.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We should be mindful when holding the creative tension. It can be reduced in two ways. 1-) lowering the vision. 2-) Getting closer to the vision. 2 is always harder than 1. We &lt;strong&gt;shift the burden&lt;/strong&gt; by symptomatic solutions in order to reduce the emotional tension (not thinking about our vision or lowering the vision).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="failure"&gt;Failure&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is not about what the vision is, it is more about what the vision does. E.g. Head of Xerox R &amp;amp; D had the vision to revolutionize the education system by having devices for students and teachers. But he ended up creating PC. Did he fail? NBA player who was the MVP 12 / 13 times in his team used to watch himself after every match and rate his play. His maximum score in his career was 65. Did he fail?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Failure is an evidence of gap between current reality and vision. Opportunity for learning. They are not about unworthiness or powerlessness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mastery of Creative Tension, builds patience and perseverance. This changes the approach to failures. The more clear picture of the current reality we can get to, the more clearly we can understand how we can reach our vision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="structural-conflict"&gt;Structural Conflict&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Structural Conflicts are byproducts of our emotional tension due to the gap between current reality and vision. The most two common underlying emotions that it triggers are powerlessness and unworthiness for the vision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We employ 3 habitual strategies to address structural conflicts:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Erode the vision.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Conflict manipulation: Avoiding, negative vision, …&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Willpower: Pushing our way through the conflict. Has very small leverage.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Author faces a situation where the people continuously let him down during the critical time in the projects. He willpowers his way through the project with the mental model that people always let other people down. Once the conflict is recognized he can develop coping strategies by setting better goals, reducing the pressure on people etc… We should be aware that we can't make the choice to change unless we are aware of our current reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pretty much all of us develop these responses through our development and experiences. In order to change these habitual responses, we need to change our sub-conscious beliefs that we are unworthy of our vision or powerless to achieve that vision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So where is the leverage?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="commitment-to-the-truth"&gt;Commitment to the Truth&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The way to change any underlying belief is being committed to the truth. (Same idea that meditators reached and explained a little further long time ago)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commitment to the Truth, doesn't mean seeking the absolute final word or ultimate cause. It is the relentless effort to understand structures underlying the events in the world and in ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A person with high level of personal mastery:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;See more of the structural conflicts underlying their own behavior.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id="using-the-subconscious"&gt;Using the Subconscious&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Subconscious is continuously learning. By focusing on the interaction between conscious and subconscious we can improve our learning (Now welcome to Daniel Kahneman's ideas). As we deepen our rapport between conscious and subconscious, we can teach it more complex tasks like detecting certain structural conflicts which in the end improves personal mastery further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Focusing on the desired result&lt;/strong&gt; for example is a skill. Once we learn this skill and once we pick an intrinsic personal vision, our subconscious keep our focus on our vision continuously. We focus and perform better when we truly care about the desired outcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="practicing-personal-mastery"&gt;Practicing Personal Mastery&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Practicing Personal Mastery creates more than trivial results in individuals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Sufi story talks about a blind man and a crippled man getting out of a forest by blind man carrying the crippled man and crippled man telling where to go. Crippled man represents the intuition and the blind man represents reason. We will find our way out when two are integrated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Practicing personal mastery doesn't aim to integrate the reason and intuition but they achieve it naturally. The integration is not one or the other at a time. Systems thinking helps with the integration by providing the language to folks to explain intuitions with reason.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="connectedness"&gt;Connectedness&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we understand the explanations of intuitions, we see that we do not exist in a different place than the external world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The story of the baby who happens to hold on to his ear and experiences discomfort without being aware of the fact that he himself is causing the discomfort. He pulls harder to get rid of the discomfort only to make things worse. When he discovers that he doesn't do it again. But as he grows up he starts taking a lot of the things in the world as given and ends up as all of us losing the connection between our actions and the external world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="compassion"&gt;Compassion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we discover our connectedness and more and more structural processes; compassion is automatic. We begin to see all of use are trapped in structures, structures that are both embedded in our thinking and in our interpersonal social lives. Once we see that we are part of systems that dictate our behavior, compassion comes up by its own rather than feelings of anger and blame.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="commitment-to-the-whole"&gt;Commitment to the Whole&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And with compassion, we are automatically drawn to the whole. We don't see self motivated goals worthy of being our visions anymore. Our personal visions automatically become more intrinsic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="fostering-personal-mastery"&gt;Fostering Personal Mastery&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want people not to develop their personal mastery, just force them. For sure it will backfire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fostering it requires setting up a right environment for people to be able to develop their skills and being a role model.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Peter M. Senge - The Fifth Discipline - Part 2</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://serdars.github.io/2014/12/18/peter-m-senge-the-fifth-discipline-part-2.html"/>
    <id>https://serdars.github.io/2014/12/18/peter-m-senge-the-fifth-discipline-part-2.html</id>
    <published>2014-12-17T18:15:00-08:00</published>
    <updated>2014-12-18T00:10:52-08:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Serdar Sutay</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Notes and commentary on &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peter_Senge"&gt;Peter M. Senge's&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/The-Fifth-Discipline-Practice-Organization/dp/0553456342"&gt;The Fifth Discipline&lt;/a&gt; continues with the basics of the fifth discipline: Systems Thinking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Notes and commentary on &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peter_Senge"&gt;Peter M. Senge's&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/The-Fifth-Discipline-Practice-Organization/dp/0553456342"&gt;The Fifth Discipline&lt;/a&gt; continues with the basics of the fifth discipline: Systems Thinking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="laws-of-the-fifth-discipline"&gt;Laws of the Fifth Discipline&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Today's problems come from yesterday's solutions: Today's problems are often caused by the partial solutions we have done to yesterday's problems.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The harder you push, the harder the system pushes back: One of our instincts to try a solution harder when it is not enough to fix a problem. Government's bail out program by its own doesn't solve the fundamental problem. It only makes them need more bail outs.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Behavior grows better before it grows worse: After a partial solution you will see the situation improving slightly before it gets worse. Slight improvement is only temporary symptomatic fix before the underlying cause kicks in again, in a more strong way.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The easy way out usually leads back in: To feel comfortable, we most of the time apply familiar solutions to the problems we face rather than looking for the real root cause and dealing with it.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The cure can be worse than the disease: Most of the times, symptomatic solutions strengthen the underlying cause or create even bigger problems.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Faster is slower: Fastest way is the most commonly requested way in today's world. But it is not necessarily the best way. Optimal rate is most of the time not the fastest way.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cause and effect are not closely related in time and space: Most of the time effects of our actions are visible sometime in the future and when that time comes we forget the action we have done in the past to see the connection.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Small changes can produce big results - but the areas of highest leverage are often least obvious.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You can have your cake and eat it too - but not at once: Sometimes dilemmas present themselves as problems but they are an artifact of &lt;strong&gt;snapshot thinking rather than process thinking&lt;/strong&gt;. E.g. increasing the quality and decreasing the costs is not achievable when you think in terms of snapshots. Investing in training and testing can increase the quality and the costs. But overtime when the effects of these changes kick in, costs will be decreased due to reduced re-work, low level of defects, etc…&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Dividing an elephant in half does not produce two small elephants: Dividing a big problem into two most of the time doesn't produce two smaller problems. It changes the nature of the original problem and makes it impossible to track the root cause.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There is no blame: When there is blame, there is "us" vs "them". Systems thinking requires to think ourselves and external entities as parts of a single system.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id="a-shift-of-mind"&gt;A Shift of Mind&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We live in an extremely complex world which is getting more and more complex every day. There are few reasons that prevents us to analyze and understand the systems we live in:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Separating the parts from the whole. Analyzing them and expecting to combine our analysis to explain to whole.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Letting go of responsibility saying "It is the way system is" or "System is too complex for me".&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the time we think in a linear way:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;Terrorist Attacks -&amp;gt; Threat to Americans -&amp;gt; Need to respond militarily&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we see only part of the problem. We miss the part of:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;US Military Activity -&amp;gt; Perceived aggressiveness of US -&amp;gt; Terrorist Recruits -&amp;gt; Terrorist Attacks&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Linear thinking only deals with the variables at hand. It deals with &lt;strong&gt;detail complexity&lt;/strong&gt;. There is a second type of complexity, &lt;strong&gt;dynamic complexity&lt;/strong&gt;, where cause and effect are subtle and distributed over time. Real leverage most of the time lies in understanding the dynamic complexity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Systems Thinking gives us a framework in order to be able to understand and analyze the system as a whole. It enables us to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;See interrelationships rather than linear cause-effect chains&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;See processes of change rather than snapshots.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It starts with &lt;strong&gt;feedback&lt;/strong&gt; concept and aims to recognize the types of structures or &lt;strong&gt;patterns&lt;/strong&gt; that occur again and again. It builds up a language with vocabulary that makes it easy to talk about systems and their composition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="words-of-the-language"&gt;Words of the Language&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Systems are made up of circles but we see them as straight lines. Circles are simple ways to represent feedback inside a system. For e.g.:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Example" src="/2014/12/18/peter-m-senge-the-fifth-discipline-part-2/basic.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the systems perspective, the human actor is part of the feedback process, not standing apart from it. This view shifts the way we are seeing our selves. Everyone shares the responsibility of the behaviors of the system, benefits as well as problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two distinct types of feedback loops:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reinforcing&lt;/strong&gt; (positive, amplifying) Non-Stable, Asymptotical Growth&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Balancing&lt;/strong&gt; (stabilizing) Stable&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many feedback processes also contain &lt;strong&gt;delays&lt;/strong&gt;. The way to think about delays is to insert "things will happen eventually" on the influence line. Delays most of the time cause fluctuations before reaching the stable point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the nature, prety much all of the reinforcing processes have a counteracting balancing process. Balancing processes are said to have their own agendas or goals. However the stabilizing point of the process is not directly determined by the goals of the individual actors in it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="sentences-of-the-language"&gt;Sentences of the Language&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sentences also called &lt;strong&gt;System Archetypes&lt;/strong&gt; are the common patterns that can be detected in the world. They are simple in their nature but we can see them all around us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="limits-to-growth"&gt;Limits to Growth&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A reinforcing process is set in motion to produce a desired result. After creating a spiral of success it creates inadvertant side effects which manifests as a balancing process and limits the growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Management Principle:&lt;/strong&gt; Don't push growth. Remove the factors limiting growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Example" src="/2014/12/18/peter-m-senge-the-fifth-discipline-part-2/limits-to-growth.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pattern of Behavior:&lt;/strong&gt; In this process, limit gradually becomes more powerful. Eventually growth can slow and reinforcing process can start turning it back. You can see minor fluctuations if there are some solution attempts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Leverage:&lt;/strong&gt; In these situations, instinctive behavior is to try to push harder. But the leverage is in the balancing loop. To change the behavior of the system identify and change or &lt;strong&gt;influence&lt;/strong&gt; the limiting factor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="shifting-the-burden"&gt;Shifting the Burden&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An underlying problem generates symptoms that demand attention. But the underlying problem is difficult to discover or address (costly, cultural blocks, etc…) so people shift the burden to other solutions. Well intentioned but can only cure the symptoms temporarily. As underlying problem grows worse, and it mostly does, the impact will be felt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Management Principle:&lt;/strong&gt; Beware symptomatic solution. Only use it to remediate the pain if it is inevitable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Example" src="/2014/12/18/peter-m-senge-the-fifth-discipline-part-2/shifting-the-burden.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pattern of Behavior:&lt;/strong&gt; The best example is alcoholism. The size of the symptomatic response will grow over time as the underlying cause gets worse and worse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Leverage:&lt;/strong&gt; Leverage is in strengthening the fundamental response and weakening the symptomatic response. Communicating the symptomatic responses and fundamental responses help. Fundamental responses require long term orientation and shared vision. Symptomatic responses are needed only if the situation is dire and should be used temporarily.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="paragraphs-of-the-language"&gt;Paragraphs of the Language&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One can form paragraphs using these sentences now. An example is a Company who creates a reinforcing process by utilizing a novel technology and achieves growth and faces a balancing process when it runs out of manufacturing capacity. They slowly erode their goals in delivery time which leads to frustrated customers and lower the sales numbers. However since the delivery time erosion is gradual (boiling frog syndrome) they don't realize it. They only see the decreased sales numbers and push more marketing strategies to increase them back up. Symptomatic solutions do not provide fixes to the underlying fundamental problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is actually another systems archetype called &lt;strong&gt;Growth and Underinvestment&lt;/strong&gt;. One would question how generalizable these archetypes are. But the important bit is that using the concepts as the language, our situation can be defined and talked about.  Without systems thinking it is hard to argue that the fundamental issue is the frustration about the delivery time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is hard to argue with the principle of leverage. We all know the metaphor of not being able to see the forest for the trees. Unfortunately when we step back sometimes we still don't see the forest, we only see trees. Systems thinking provides us the language to be able to see the forest and the trees at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Mahzarin Banaji - Blindspot</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://serdars.github.io/2014/12/12/mahzarin-banaji-blindspot.html"/>
    <id>https://serdars.github.io/2014/12/12/mahzarin-banaji-blindspot.html</id>
    <published>2014-12-11T16:55:00-08:00</published>
    <updated>2014-12-11T17:25:20-08:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Serdar Sutay</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mahzarin_Banaji"&gt;Mahzarin Banaji&lt;/a&gt;'s book &lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/Blindspot-Hidden-Biases-Good-People/dp/0553804642"&gt;Blindspot&lt;/a&gt; is an easily approachable book that discusses the biases we all carry subconsciously. For a more in depth study of the topic Kahneman's &lt;strong&gt;Thinking Fast and Slow&lt;/strong&gt; is a more appropriate book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Banaji calls the biases &lt;strong&gt;MindBugs&lt;/strong&gt;. </summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mahzarin_Banaji"&gt;Mahzarin Banaji&lt;/a&gt;'s book &lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/Blindspot-Hidden-Biases-Good-People/dp/0553804642"&gt;Blindspot&lt;/a&gt; is an easily approachable book that discusses the biases we all carry subconsciously. For a more in depth study of the topic Kahneman's &lt;strong&gt;Thinking Fast and Slow&lt;/strong&gt; is a more appropriate book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Banaji calls the biases &lt;strong&gt;MindBugs&lt;/strong&gt;.  They can be classified into two: Personal vs Social. She goes into a lot of details around memory on the Personal side and stereotypes and race on the social side. Here is a very high level summary:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Memory is a tricky tool. Most of the times when we retrieve something from our memory, we find ourselves pretty confident about it. However in reality this is far from truth. Memory doesn't work as a computer hard disk. It doesn't store an experience and play it back exactly as it is. It stores the experience in relationship to all other previous experiences and mental models we have in our minds and it retrieves similarly. Here is an example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People watching a video of a car crash remember the event differently when asked about "Do you recall how the blue car smashed into the red car?" vs "Do you recall the how blue car accidentally hit the red car?". They also form different initial opinions / prejudices against the driver of the blue car based on the question they are asked. This is called Retroactive Interference. An event interferes with the memory of a different event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can recall things with higher repetition more easily therefore we are more confident about the details of these memories. Vividness also increases the availability of the events from memory. It is more easier to remember "how I splashed wine over the pure white carpet violently when leaving the room" than "how I throw the wine glass to the floor when leaving the room".&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it comes to social biases, we all prefer and associate things based on personal and collective historical experiences. It is proven with Implicit Association Tests (IATs) that pretty much all of us has racial and gender associations (even feminists). However note that discriminatory behavior is not necessarily directly correlated with having an implicit association.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;
A man and his son are driving to a championship football game. On the road, they crash into a car. The father is killed instantly, and the son, critically injured, is rushed to the hospital. As the medics rush the son to the operating room, the doctor walks in and say’s, “I can’t operate, that’s my son”.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How could this be true?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stereotypes are both true and false. They are a byproduct of our minds which is continuously classifying information in the world into certain buckets. They change over time. They are mostly negative (I'm fully bought into this idea). They can be harmful to our society because they impact convictions of judges, treatment of doctors. They can be also harmful to ourselves because they can turn into self fulfilling prophecies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interestingly according to a study Turkish stereotype in 1930s was in the order of priority:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cruel, very religious, treacherous, sensual, ignorant.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Same study found out the Turkish stereotype in 2001 to be:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Very religious, extremely nationalistic, tradition loving, quick tempered, aggressive.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Peter M. Senge - The Fifth Discipline - Part 1</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://serdars.github.io/2014/12/11/peter-m-senge-the-fifth-discipline-part-1.html"/>
    <id>https://serdars.github.io/2014/12/11/peter-m-senge-the-fifth-discipline-part-1.html</id>
    <published>2014-12-11T00:24:00-08:00</published>
    <updated>2014-12-11T00:35:53-08:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Serdar Sutay</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Notes and commentary on &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peter_Senge"&gt;Peter M. Senge's&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/The-Fifth-Discipline-Practice-Organization/dp/0553456342"&gt;The Fifth Discipline&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Notes and commentary on &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peter_Senge"&gt;Peter M. Senge's&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/The-Fifth-Discipline-Practice-Organization/dp/0553456342"&gt;The Fifth Discipline&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Five Disciplines represent approaches for developing three core learning capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fostering Aspiration
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Personal Mastery&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Shared Vision&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Reflective Conversation
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Mental Models&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Dialogue&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Understanding Complexity
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Systems Thinking&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deming points out that management systems and our education systems are very much alike. The 8 elements that Deming points out under the context of Total Quality Management can be applied to education systems as well:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Management by Measurement: Focusing on short-term metrics, Devaluing intangibles.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Compliance-based cultures: Management by fear. (Again more Ken Robinson’s talk.)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Managing outcomes: Management sets targets. People are accountable reaching them without the permission to change the system.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Right Answers vs Wrong Answers: Technical Problem Solving is emphasized.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Uniformity: Superficial agreement is more important than conflict.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Predictability / Controllability: Holy Trinity of Management: Plan - Organize - Control.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Excessive competitiveness and distrust: Competition is essential to outcome and innovation.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Loss of the whole: Fragmentation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id="how-our-actions-create-our-reality-and-how-can-we-change-it"&gt;How our actions create our reality… and how can we change it?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="five-disciplines"&gt;Five Disciplines&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For an innovation to occur you need more than 1 piece of technology. Consumerization of the aircraft required 5 technologies: variable-pitch propeller, landing gear, light-wieghted body, radial air-cooled engine and wing flaps. Without wing flaps Boeing couldn’t successfully innovate 1 year before McDouglas. Similarly a learning organization needs to master 5 separate but re-inforcing skills:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Personal Mastery: Discipline of continuously clarifying and deepening our vision.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mental Models: Deeply ingrained assumptions, generalizations, even pictures &amp;amp; images that influence how we understand the world. Working with mental models require us to turn the mirror to inside, i.e. trying to understand how we understand things.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Building a Shared Vision: Unearthing shared “pictures of the future” that foster genuine commitment and enrollment rather than compliance.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Team Learning: Capacity to make “dialogue”, to suspend assumptions and enter into a thinking mode. When possible IQ of the team becomes higher than the individuals forming the team however this happens seldomly.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Systems Thinking: As a Toyota manager pointed out, West does all the things we do but still can not reach similar results. Because in addition to having individual components, bringing them together as a whole is another requirement. This is why System Thinking, the binding discipline is the Fifth Discipline.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What do we mean by learning is really important. It is not reading a book, passing your class, getting AA from the exam, getting a plus from your teacher, promoting to Senior Software Engineer. In addition to these, it is internalizing a certain piece of information, working on adopting this information and changing your behavior along this information. You don’t learn bicycle riding after reading a book. Learning is getting to the heart of it and also of ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="learning-disabilities"&gt;Learning Disabilities&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I am my position: In our jobs, most of us see ourselves in a system on which we have no influence. We describe the task we do day to day, not the purpose of the greater enterprise.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The enemy is out there: When we think ourselves as our jobs, as a result we think that enemy is out there when something goes wrong. We don’t generally see the secondary (or further) consequences of our actions beyond our immediate circle.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The illusion of taking charge: Taking aggressive action against an external entity during crisis is not really being proactive. Most of the times pro-activeness is reactiveness is disguise. True pro-activeness comes from seeing how we contribute to our own problems.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The fixation on events: When two children get into a fight it goes like “But, he hit my ball” / “But he broke my toy” / “But he called me …” Focusing on the events distract us from seeing the longer-term patterns of change that lie behind the events.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The parable of the boiled frog: We can not escape the fate of boiled frog until we slow down and see the gradual processes that often pose great threats.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The delusion of learning from experience: True learning comes from experience. But if we can not observe the consequences of our actions (because they are in distant feature or they are in a separate part of the organization), we can’t learn from them. Each of us has a “learning horizon”. Cycles are especially hard to see. For e.g. due to lack of chip designers, most of the students are going into chip design which over-saturates chip designers when they are graduating which makes very few people to go into it which results in a shortage after 4 years etc…&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The myth of the management team: The management team who should be able to fight these disabilities generally end up fighting for turf, trying to save their image… They operate well under routine conditions but their “team-ness” goes away when under pressure.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id="prisoners-of-the-system-or-prisoners-of-our-own-thinking"&gt;Prisoners of the system or prisoners of our own thinking?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beer_distribution_game"&gt;Beer Distribution Game&lt;/a&gt;: Composed of Retailer / Wholesaler / Brewery. An advertisement bumps the customer demand by 100%. This creates a cycles of inventory shortages followed by over-stocking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Independent of the people who are playing the game, the end result is generally the same. Players end up blaming each other and assume their problems are due to fluctuating customer demand even tough in reality it is stable. The lesson is that structure of the system influences the behaviors of the players. There are good strategies to play but we don’t stop &amp;amp; think to find them. Structure in human systems is subtle and leverage most of the time comes from new ways of thinking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tolstoy argues that Napoleon wasn’t the cause of the Wars / Revolution. History, and many number of individuals created Napoleon then took him down. (Salut to Geopolitics concept). “Structure” used here doesn’t mean the organization chart or logical structure. It points to the “key interrelationships that influence behavior over time”. E.g. “delay in the delivery from wholesaler to retailer” increases “the order of retailers from the wholesaler”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to be successful, one must re-define their scope of influence. Your influence is broader than the limits of your position. Retailer can influence suppliers behavior by placing orders or not. “Either the large system works, or your position will not work."&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Systems perspective shows us that there are multiple levels of explanation in any complex situation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Systemic Structure - generative -&amp;gt; Patterns of Behavior - responsive -&amp;gt; Events - reactive&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since event explanations are the most common in contemporary culture, reactive management prevails. Behavior pattern explanations focus on seeing long term trends and assessing their implications. E.g. distributions systems are prone to instability which becomes more severe the further you move away from the retailer. This level helps us understand and respond to shifting trends. Structural explanation is the least command and most powerful. They explain the causes of the patterns of behavior. Franklin Roosevelt explained how the banking system worked in a public speech about why “Bank Holiday” is happening and was successful in shifting the negative public view on the topic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we understand the structure of the system that causes its behavior, we can clearly see our power to change that behavior. Most of the time we discover something similar to what Walt Kelly discovered in Pogo:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We have met the enemy and he is us."&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Tom DeMarco - Peopleware</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://serdars.github.io/2014/12/07/tom-demarco-peopleware.html"/>
    <id>https://serdars.github.io/2014/12/07/tom-demarco-peopleware.html</id>
    <published>2014-12-07T14:49:00-08:00</published>
    <updated>2014-12-11T00:27:40-08:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Serdar Sutay</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Some notes and commentary from &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tom_DeMarco"&gt;Tom DeMarco's&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/Peopleware-Productive-Projects-Second-Edition/dp/0932633439"&gt;Peopleware&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Some notes and commentary from &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tom_DeMarco"&gt;Tom DeMarco's&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/Peopleware-Productive-Projects-Second-Edition/dp/0932633439"&gt;Peopleware&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="team-sociology"&gt;Team Sociology&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Majority of the problems that stand between a project and success are generally not technical problems but sociological ones. &lt;strong&gt;Politics&lt;/strong&gt; is not the right word when talking about these problems. This word is used when we don't want to engage with some problems. We classify them as institutional, un-fixable and classify them under &lt;strong&gt;Politics&lt;/strong&gt; to excuse ourselves from attempting to solve them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="theory-of-values"&gt;Theory of Values&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There have been two theories of value historically. Spanish Theory of Value stated that there is a fixed amount of value on the Earth so the way to extract more value is to try to be more efficient when using resources. English Theory of Value stated that additional value can be obtained by ingenuity and technology. Spain ended up going around the world to try to extract more value from land. English went through the industrial revolution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="efficiency--productivity"&gt;Efficiency &amp;amp; Productivity&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are most efficient &amp;amp; productive when we are in &lt;strong&gt;flow&lt;/strong&gt;. This is the state where we are spending effort effortlessly, not aware of the time and our surroundings and focusing on one thing only without any interruptions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The traditional methods to boost efficiency &amp;amp; productivity (like overtime, long hours, etc…) are only useful for a short amount of time. They are like sprinting. If we are sprinting all the time, we will get tired. We will not be working better we will only be working faster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is important to try to maximize the uninterrupted hours in order to boost productivity. (See email and meetings section as well.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="deadlines--pressure"&gt;Deadlines / Pressure&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Parkinson's Law: Some British dude Parkinson theorized that work expands the time allocated for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thankfully Parkinson's Law and the Spanish Value Theory is not attempted in most of the organizations nowadays. Phony deadlines are still used as a mutated form of the Parkinson's law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When all the team knows that a deadline is phony, there is no reason for a manager to stick with it other than insecurity and neediness. Rather than attempting to create pressure (which decreases the productivity), a manager should be able to create a common sense of a goal for team to align at (which increases productivity).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="quality"&gt;Quality&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the builders take pride in the work we do. We would like our work to shine and get used by many people. No one wants to build a low quality piece of software and watch people use it. We have internal quality requirements for the software we are building. This level is both rational and emotional. We set ourselves for the future by ensuring we have strong enough technical roots from which our tree can grow. We also form a connection between the quality of the thing we're building and our abilities as a builder. The lower the quality, the worse our perception will be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Swimming against this natural flow of quality, most of the times due to pressure to ship, is counter-productive. Not only because it sets the team up to spend more time supporting &amp;amp; maintaining a low quality product but also it de-motivates the team since team now views itself as a low quality team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="corporate-entropy"&gt;Corporate Entropy&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Entropy is the level of sameness. In corporations similar to the universe, entropy always increases. The higher the entropy, the lower the chances of great energy and creative work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="office-environment"&gt;Office Environment&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many factors in an office environment that might impact a team. Not surprisingly, curiosity of many failed to find a direct link between any aspect of an environment and productivity. But there are a few things to keep in mind when thinking about the physical environment:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Privacy: &lt;strong&gt;Flow&lt;/strong&gt; is only possible in silent spots with minimized distractions and with privacy.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Having people working together close is preferred since it helps them build relationships.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Entropy in a physical environment is a subconscious sign of entropy in the culture of the company. It should be watched out.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Every one works better in an environment that they can tailor to their specific needs. When teams are doing this, it is a great sign of developing team identity.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(As always) Christopher Alexander's Organic Order Theory provides some patterns to be included in an environment for different needs of teams:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tailored workspace from a kit.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Windows&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Public Space&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Teams can find more for themselves if they think.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Environment is always in evolution. The thing to watch out for is the signs of distress in it. E.g. people reserving conference room in order to hide and work, listening music with speaker phones to control white noise and interruptive noise, etc… These can be signs of limitations in the environment or in a bigger scope.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="people"&gt;People&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The high level strategy recommended can be summarized as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Get the right people.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Make them happy so they don't leave&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Turn them loose.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rather than connectionless aptitude tests, technical questions with yes no answers, and out of the box packages; it is important to try to measure the connection between the candidate and the team. If a team is forming an identity, ensuring this identity is coherent when hiring is important. Also hiring is a great tool to decrease the entropy of teams when needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From accounting point of view it is different to give $100 to utilities and to buy a server. Server is part of infrastructure so it is not a direct expense. Similar way of thinking should be applied to human capital. Investing in a conference or training is not necessarily a direct expense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When people leave, or company downsizes, there are hidden costs in the system for teams. Assuming a replacement is found immediately, obvious one is the ramp up time for the new comer as well as extra time needed from the members to mentor the new comer. Less obvious one is the risk to team relationships and recovery of the normalness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Watching the turnover rate is a must for every manager. Great teams have low turn over rates. People behave as if they are not expected to leave. In normal teams people leave because:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;No long term involvement and no reason for long term involvement with the job.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Feeling of disposability.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Seeing loyalty as reasonless.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id="jelled-team"&gt;Jelled Team&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jelled Team is a highly functioning team. They have a sense of identity. Individuals have goals and these are aligned with the team's goals. Members have a sense of eliteness and when doing their jobs they enjoy themselves. A great example is Black Team @ IBM. Sense of eliteness may lead to turning the team into a clique. This is something to be watched for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The job of the manager is not to lead the team. It is to remove the blocks in the team's road and prepare the rest of the teams for this team's momentum. The things a manager can do to kill these types of teams are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Defensive Management: When manager doesn't trust his team members, he is in trouble. Without autonomy jelled teams are unachievable.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bureaucracy: Unnecessary process, documentation will slow a team down and decrease the motivation of individual members.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Physical Separation:&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Time Fragmentation: Flow breaker, productivity killer and demoralizer due to decreased amount of perceived progress. The biggest sin of all.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Quality:&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Phony Deadlines:&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Clique Control: Breaking up a team during their momentum building stage.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coaching and leadership in jelled teams are not done by a single person. Since members complete each other, they also coach each other in the areas that they are strong at.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Competition is tricky. It can be good or bad based on the situation. One of the possible things that can kill a team is the performance ratings though. Any action that rewards team members differentially is likely to foster adversary competition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One can't put together jelled team all the time but they can increase the chances of a team getting jelled up. A few things one can do are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Trusting team members.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sensible subordination: Knowing when to break the rules.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Augmenting / protecting team identity &amp;amp; feeling of eliteness&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Natural authority: Manager doesn't invoke the power given to her from the upper levels.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Providing satisfying closure: As human being we all need some reassurance that we're headed in the right direction.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Structured as a network, not a hierarchy: There is no permanent leader. Depending on the situation each person leads at different times.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id="leadership"&gt;Leadership&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A manager invites her team to her place for a dinner. When people show up they drink a couple of beers and chat. Manager admits that she didn't have time to prep a dinner and says that we should be talented enough to put together a spaghetti dinner. Without any further directions and one fellow starts on the salad and the other is putting together a sauce. The new comer offers his signature garlic bread. Manager chimes in when someone needs the onions cut. They eat until they are full and get started on the cleaning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Manager's effort is invisible. It all seems natural. Good managers provide opportunities for teams to succeed together (periodic demos are an example of this kind) and build momentum. They have a subconscious understanding / feeling of what's good for the team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="risk"&gt;Risk&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the great things that can be done with low risk is already done. One needs to question what he is doing if there is no risk involved. One risk that we do never manage is our own failure. This is not fun since working in case you fail is demotivating. This should only be done when the consequences of our failure is so dire that they can not be contained.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="meetings"&gt;Meetings&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are all aware of the potential meeting hell we can fall into anytime. One of the tricks to see if a meeting is a working meeting or non-working meeting is to check if "What needs to happen for this meeting to end?" question can be answered. Some examples of non-working meeting are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ceremonies: Mostly due to defensive management, where manager talks with each member one by one and forces the others to listen. Mostly to assert the manager-ness.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Laptop Meetings: Where everyone works on the laptops.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Visibility Meetings: In order for people to increase their visibility across the organization.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id="corporate-spam-and-silent-consent"&gt;Corporate Spam and Silent Consent&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similar to unnecessary meetings, our email is also filled with unnecessary emails. Most of the reasons why we have so many are similar with the reasons we have many meetings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An important note for emails is the "silent consent". The default rule in corporations is that if you're included in an email chain and if you don't raise your voice, you specify your consent. This results in defensive emailing in order to make sure that you don't give your consent to things that you don't want to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also the missing trust between the manager and the team members cause a lot  of unnecessary &lt;strong&gt;FYI&lt;/strong&gt; email traffic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="change"&gt;Change&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Human beings detest change. We work against this force when trying to change the way people interact with the world. We also detest change in workplace. When we encounter or propose a change there are 3 fundamental response types:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Blindly loyal (asks no questions)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Believers but Questioners
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Skeptics (Show me)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Passive Observers (What's in it for me?)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Opposed (Fear of Change)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Opposed (Fear of loss of power)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Militantly Opposed (will undermine and destroy)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Success depends on the way "Believers but Questioners" are handled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We think that change is modeled this way:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;
Old Status Quo ---(A better idea)--&amp;gt; New Status Quoa
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However a more close approximation is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;
Old Status Quo ---(Foreign Element)---&amp;gt; Chaos --(Transforming Idea)---&amp;gt;
  Practice and Integration ---&amp;gt; New Status Quo
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being aware of this model helps us with the changes. One last thing to note about change is that in order for any change to be effective, &lt;code&gt;failure&lt;/code&gt; should be an option. People should feel safe to make mistakes otherwise risk aversion will prevent any change in its infancy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="organizational-learning"&gt;Organizational Learning&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a difference between Experience and Learning. Definition of learning also includes the incorporation of whatever is the thing one is learning into their lives. At organizational level this means an organization changes its behavior based on the experiences and findings it makes. This is a long subject that we will cover in detail in the Fifth Discipline book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But a critical question authors point out is &lt;strong&gt;where&lt;/strong&gt; it happens in an organization. Since top management is too high to see the day to day things and individual contributors are too busy with the day to day things, the only place there this can happen is middle management. And for this to happen, middle management should be talking to each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="various"&gt;Various&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Coding War Games: Where the authors put developers against each other to code a component indicated that people from the same company ended up having similar results. Authors conclude that good engineers are in good companies and mediocre ones are in mediocre companies. A better way of saying this IMO is, an engineering team is successful when it can ensure the good engineers come and stay in it.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gilb's Law: Anything you need to quantify can be measured in some way that it superior to not measuring at all.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;E-factor: Uninterrupted Hours / Body-Present Hours&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Deterministic vs Non-Deterministic Systems: Deterministic systems can not self-heal since there is no human being present at the time. Automating all the things is not the right solution. With a process (methodology) one needs to be aware of this and ensures that opportunities to heal an automated system are possible and easy.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Early Overstaffing: A good way to waste time. In general for most of the projects, at the beginning it's much easier to go with a small number of people.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
