<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Blog Name</title>
  <subtitle>Blog subtitle</subtitle>
  <id>http://blog.url.com/</id>
  <link href="http://blog.url.com/"/>
  <link href="http://blog.url.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <updated>2014-08-13T17:52:00-07:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Blog Author</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>About Beginnings</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/2014/08/14/about-beginnings.html"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/2014/08/14/about-beginnings.html</id>
    <published>2014-08-13T17:52:00-07:00</published>
    <updated>2014-08-16T01:40:58-07:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Sometimes we make a big deal out of beginnings. We put together detailed plans, prepare ourselves to bravely execute before beginning something. And we expect to feel differently right after them. After all we are not the same person anymore after beginning that thing. The world is a different place now. Or is it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes we are scared of them. We need to think it through and convince ourselves that it is OK to begin. What if this happens? What if it does not go well? What would other people think of me now that I am doing this? Maybe we are not scared of beginnings but ourselves. Most of the time we don't begin because of this fear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes we trick ourselves into believing that we will begin soon. We research, draft plans, talk to people, write documents… We obsess about them. We imagine ourselves doing it. The pleasure of doing that thing without investing the required effort is sweet, but short lived. We never begin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the reason we make a big deal out of beginnings is rooted in the way we see ourselves. We envision ourselves as unchanging entities and we see beginnings as times when we make a conscious decision to change. How can we make such a change easily without preparing ourselves for it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reality is that we are constantly changing. Beginnings are minor shifts in the constant stream of changes. One needs to stick with them in order to make a major change. I.e. we are not black or white. We are gray with a constantly changing shade. Beginnings are the small shifts that we intentionally make in our shade. And things get a lot easier when we don't make a big deal out of beginnings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="directional-vs-result-based-thinking"&gt;Directional vs Result Based Thinking&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was a TED talk (which I'm not able to find anymore) talking about how our happiness is affected by the way we're trying to achieve our goals. One way is to set a goal, e.g. being a CEO; do anything and everything you can to get to it; and measure yourself based on if you were able to reach that goal or not. Another way is to treat your goal as an aspiration and set yourself smaller goals that progressively gets you closer to it; and measure yourself based on how close you get to your aspiration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Different Paths" class="visual" src="/2014/08/14/about-beginnings/different_paths.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Say you aspire to write a novel; a successful one. The starting poing it Google: "How to write a novel". While you're at it you order the two recommended books and read them. You brainstorm to find an idea worthy of being a novel. You prepare a few character sheets and draft a storyline. Then you worry about miserably failing and go to Google: "How to get published". You start learning about the tricks that makes a novel readable. You start thinking about if these tricks are inline with your philosophy of writing. Then you go back to your draft storyline. You don't like it. Suddenly other things start creeping in your life and you don't have any time to write your novel anymore. Not only you didn't get any closer to your goal, you've also wasted a lot of time. And the worst part is writing a novel still seems to you like a potential goal only reachable if you didn't need to do these other things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="steering"&gt;Steering&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using the second way, you can begin tomorrow by writing a story and having your friends read it. Then you can write a longer story and see the sacrifices required to write a novel. Maybe you can write a short draft and get it to a few people in the publishing industry and see what they think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe you will discover that writing a novel is your over-romanticised dream. Short stories are a better fit for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Moving Path" class="visual" src="/2014/08/14/about-beginnings/moving_goal.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Change the route. Collect the best short stories you have already written. Write a few more and see if this is your true passion. Maybe after writing a few more it gets boring just like the novel You like writing about real things. Change direction again. Write a few articles for internet magazines and send them. See if you would like that. Who knows, maybe you'll discover that drinking better beer is the most important thing in life while covering a Beer Festival. Finally you have an enjoyable passion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now you might ask what if I end up going around and around getting nowhere? You can cross that bridge too when you get there. Don't fall into the trap of getting stuck at the port.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="begin-now"&gt;Begin Now!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many ideas are based on not making a big deal out of beginnings. Lean startup, waterfall vs agile, prototyping instead of writing a document… Planning to start a diet next Monday; start right now by not eating that bag of chips. Planning to start an exercise program, start right now by taking a 15 minutes run. Planning to start spending more time with your family, pick up the phone and call them now!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whatever it is that you are planning to begin; begin tomorrow by taking the first brave step. You will be one step closer to your destination wherever it might be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Says one who has been planning to start a blog for the last few years…&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
