<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Leaf</title>
  <subtitle>One in many, many in one.</subtitle>
  <id>https://serdars.github.io/</id>
  <link href="https://serdars.github.io/"/>
  <link href="https://serdars.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <updated>2014-11-30T18:13:00-08:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Serdar Sutay</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>Noam Chomsky - Power Systems</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://serdars.github.io/2014/12/01/noam-chomsky-power-systems.html"/>
    <id>https://serdars.github.io/2014/12/01/noam-chomsky-power-systems.html</id>
    <published>2014-11-30T18:13:00-08:00</published>
    <updated>2014-11-30T18:44:47-08:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Serdar Sutay</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A decent propaganda system doesn't announce its principles or intentions. You presuppose a framework and then people just come to accept it.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;– Noam Chomsky&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Raw notes from &lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/Power-Systems-Conversations-Democratic-Challenges/dp/0805096159/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1417400238&amp;amp;sr=8-1"&gt;Power Systems&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Noam_Chomsky"&gt;Noam Chomsky&lt;/a&gt;…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A decent propaganda system doesn't announce its principles or intentions. You presuppose a framework and then people just come to accept it.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;– Noam Chomsky&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Raw notes from &lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/Power-Systems-Conversations-Democratic-Challenges/dp/0805096159/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1417400238&amp;amp;sr=8-1"&gt;Power Systems&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Noam_Chomsky"&gt;Noam Chomsky&lt;/a&gt;…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="the-new-american-imperialism"&gt;The New American Imperialism&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Imperialism vs Settler Colonialism: Latter is the worst where the people are "exterminated" than the former.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;American decline should be taken with a grain of salt. America hit the top after WW2. At that time it had 50% of world wealth. Nowadays it has around 25%. When you portray as one should have everything, losing some might seem like a loss but indeed it is not.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Adam Smith said that "In England people who own the society make the policy and these are merchant and manufacturers." Nowadays this has changed to be financial institutions and multi-nationals. And for e.g. they have an interest in Chinese Development.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If one measures the growth correctly, not just the number of products but also the costs and benefits of making them; Chine should be rated lower than its current position in Human Development Index.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;"War is a racket. Few profit, many pay." US Major General Smedley Butler from &lt;a href="http://www.ratical.org/ratville/CAH/warisaracket.html"&gt;War is a Racket&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1915: US disbanded Haitian parliament at gunpoint, since it had refused to accept a US written constitution which enabled US corporations to buy Haitian island. Idea was that Haiti needed foreign investment to grow and US wouldn't invest if they didn't own something. Haitian people didn't understand this and parliament was dissolved. Under US control a referendum passed with 99.9% with only 5% of the population participating.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;After 9/11 Bush ordered Taliban to hand over Osama Bin Laden. They asked for evidence of his participation in 9/11. US didn't have any but reacted with contempt "How can you ask for evidence?" People are informed that bombing will start soon unless Taliban gives Osama Bin Laden. After 3 weeks British said bombing will continue unless people don't overthrow their government. Taliban might be over-thrown from within but US wanted to impose its choice of regime for Afghanistan therefore it was invaded. Similar to Iraq.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Smaller countries hire individual terrorists like Carlos the Jackal. US hires terrorist states like Israel, and sometimes Taiwan and Britain.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In US one is not supposed to use the term "working class", correct terminology is "Middle Class / Underclass".&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How Hitler was elected? Germany was under control of Hindenburg, a Prussian that had the support of bourgeois. They were not doing anything for people. Depression hit. Hitler a charismatic leader appeared to nationalism and said he can fix the problem.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Weekend protestors: People who go out protesting on the weekend and expect results thereafter. However results are not taken by sitting in front of White House for 3 weeks. They need to be consistent. However "Quick gratification culture is not conducive to that kind of commitment."&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Problem with the Democratic Party is that they can not come out and say: Look back in 1970s we've participated the major process of financialization of the economy. Wealth started to accumulate in the pockets of few. These are our policies. There is no real left but atomic groups of people with special interests such as environmentalism, gay rights, etc…&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id="chains-of-submission-and-subservience"&gt;Chains of Submission and Subservience&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mental slavery didn't replace slavery. It has always existed.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In highly democratic societies, propaganda systems are very strong because of the clear articulated recognition that people had gained so many rights that it was hard to suppress them by force.
When Britain abolished slavery officially, they still needed to run their plantations with slaves so they offered gifts and easy term for them to acquire consumer goods based with debt to plantations and system continued to work. The United Fruit company did the same thing in Central America. These techniques are as old as the world. Consumers are a lot easier to fabricate than tarter chambers.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Public education, social security are kind of concepts (principle of solidarity) that go against personal doctrine that you should just look after yourself and let everyone fall. If you are trying to maximize profits of consumption, then working together is the wrong idea. Solidarity makes people harder to control and prevents them being passive objects of private power. &lt;em&gt;[Self Note: This is very similar to the concept of polygamy vs monogamy from Red Queen. Polygamy results in few people controlling most of the mates in a society.]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id="uprisings"&gt;Uprisings&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What tips of an uprising is usually random. Like one person setting himself on fire in Tunisia. All the time however there is a lot of background leading up to it.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Arab Spring is a revolt against Western backed dictators throughout the region.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Saudi Arabia has exercised very strong violence to stop the uprising in itself and Bahrain. This didn't fly a lot in western media.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;However when the situation is delicate and you have a unreliable dictator who has plenty of oil but who was unreliable, you would want to change it with a reliable one such as the case of Libya.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Egypt and Tunisia, the game is an old one. You support a dictator until the end when he loses all the control and support. When this becomes impossible shelve him off somewhere, issue dramatic proclamations about democracy and then restore the old regime to the extent possible.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Currently still most of the energy producing countries are under western backed dictatorships. Iraq was one flowing out which was recently restored (kind of). Arab Spring's process is limited but not insignificant.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Iraq was not fully restored but this was not due to declining US economy but due to diversification of global power centers. [I.e. I can't control all the world anymore I'm losing…]&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Matthew Yglesias principle: One of the main functions of the international institutional order is precisely to legitimate the use of deadly military force by western powers.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Western countries want stability but the definition of stability is conformity to Western orders.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id="domestic-disturbances"&gt;Domestic Disturbances&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Occupy movement has succeeded in tapping feelings, attitudes and understanding that were hidden. It had progress. Obviously there was a massive propaganda to undermine it, framing it as politics of envy. "Get a shower and get a job."&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;"Occupying" was a tactic that is extremely successful. It brought people together to talk. "Atomization is a technique of control and marginalization." But every tactic has a half-life. After a while you start to see diminishing returns.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Also a lesson to learn: unless labor movement is revitalized, a movement will not go really far.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Holder vs Humanitarian Law Project Case: Humanitarian Law Project organization was giving advice to the organizations under US terrorist list on strategies of non-violence. Supreme Court said this is material advice. FBI raided members' houses for evidence, etc…&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The terrorist list is also an interesting one. One that included Nelson Mandela for a long time and one from which Saddam Hussein was removed so that US can provide him support.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Case of Omar Khadr: 15 year old boy who defended his village from invading forces in this case US Army, was taken to Guantanamo for 8 years than offered a choice either plead guilty and spend another 8 years or stay here indefinitely. Strikingly he was a Canadian citizen for which Canada has done zip.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Occupy movement's leaderless mentality was a good thing which made them prevent develop a specific line such as in order to be Republican you need to accept 10 things, no tax on wealthy, if there is someone we don't like out there we kill them… However being leaderless had the downside of having none beating drums all the time for continuity.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Howard Zinn once commented that (P78). This was echoes previously by David Hume. "Power is always on the side of the governed." In modern societies this is counter by indoctrination and pacification. Thanks to Edward Bernays.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Economics tell that markets are based on informed consumers making rational choices. But marketing is an effort that is to uniform people and have them make irrational decisions in favor of consumerism. Similarly current state of politics and voting.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Aristotle pointed out that when people have the right to vote, the majority will be the poor and they will use this right to take away property from the rich which wouldn't be fair so we have to prevent this. Aristotle tried to fix this by reducing the inequality and putting in welfare programs. James Madison faced the same problem and proposed to increase inequality with land reform back at the time. US constitution followed Madison's approach. House is closer the public with less powers. Senate was not elected had the most of the power.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;This was a failed theory. When people have the right to vote, since the majority is poor and behind in the intellectual advancement, the politicians with conservative and popular policies will always have an advantage over liberal politicians. It is up to liberal politicians to figure out a way to overcome this handicap and win the election and then implement steps to reduce this handicap for the long term.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id="unconventional-wisdom"&gt;Unconventional Wisdom&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Austerity is the worst thing you can do during a recession.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Geopolitical discussion from EU -&amp;gt; Turkey -&amp;gt; Kurds -&amp;gt; Iran -&amp;gt; India -&amp;gt; Pakistan …&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id="mental-slavery"&gt;Mental Slavery&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A decent propaganda system doesn't announce its principles or intentions. You presuppose a framework and then people just come to accept it. Soviet propaganda or Church propaganda is not highly successful because they told people what to do and believe.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In 2008, Advertising Age a marketing conference gave the best campaign award to Obama campaign.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;"Reading a book doesn't mean just turning the pages. It means thinking about it, identifying part that you want to go back to, asking how to place it in a broader context, pursuing the ideas. There is no point in reading a book it you let it pass before your eyes and then forget about it ten minutes later. You might as well not be reading."&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;One of the interesting piracy case is around pharmaceuticals. They want to prevent piracy of drugs being cheaply produced in India / China. They claim that they need the high profit margin for new research and development. (P108) According to Dean Baker, if the cost of pharmeteuitcal research was picked up by public, there would be huge cost savings because the majority of the research is done under public namespace anyways. Companies do the finishing part of the research and marketing / packaging.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;(P117) "I'm sure you get a lot of questions like 'Election is upon us Chomsky. What should I do? Vote or stay at home?' How do you respond to that?" "The first thing I say is that you should spend about 5 minutes on your question. There are much more important questions. But the question about elections doesn't require much thought. For president, there will be two candidates you don't like. One will be plausibly much more dangerous than the other. If you are in a safe state, i.e. if you know how the vote would come out you have choices. You can say "OK I won't vote or I'll vote for some party that's trying to become an independent alternative say Greens. If you're in a swing state, you have to ask yourself: Is it better to help the worse candidate to be elected? There might be a case for this."&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;"Power doesn't commit suicide." -&amp;gt; There will obviously be resistance for movement like Occupy.
Institutions currently work to maximize the show term profit and gain. This will eventually lead to destruction of environment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id="learning-how-to-discover"&gt;Learning how to discover&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Universal grammar is the study of genetic basis for language faculty.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Language faculty was developed quite recently. It's generally plausibly assumed that this happened during "the great leap forward" which is assumed to develop human creative endeavors. What happened should be pretty simple because in evolutionary time scale it happened in the blink of an eye.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;This is a topic that I digress from Chomsky.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Similar to the "Universal Genome" theory, for language research is going on about universal grammar.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Language is biologically acquired. If you get a baby from australia and being him over to US, he learns perfectly good english.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bulk of the language is learnt before age 2 event though the baby only makes two word sentences.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Deaf - Blind people can learn language by placing their hands on the face and throat of other people. P134 - P135 -&amp;gt; Story of a deaf / blind couple who live their life pretty regularly.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;"Culture influences and shapes language" -&amp;gt; is a comment but almost meaningless comment. Culture is a general term for everything that goes on. Sure everything that goes on influences language.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Vocabulary definitely is influenced from the time and environment. But this generally is trivial like if computer is invented that the people weren't talking about before, you add a word for it.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Languist is the one who studies this and linguist is the one who speaks lots of different languages.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In order to make what Chomsky do you need to exercise one muscle, the ability of being puzzled. Why do things happen this way?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gallileo was a dissident of his time. He was denounced by a lot of organizations and people because his ideas were against mainstream. Every society treats dissidents harshly. Also every society is outraged about the harsh treatment of dissidents in the enemy states.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Social solidarity is very dangerous for concentrated power. Facebook / Twitter / etc… makes it easy to organize and keep some connections alive, they contribute to atomization.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;US pioneered the mass public education. One reason is that "Mass population is getting a lot of rights. If they are not properly educated they might come after us." If you have a free education that flames creativity and independence people will still come after you. You need to have an education system that reinforces obedience, acceptance of authority and doctrine.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Pretty conspiracist. TED talk from Ken Robinson summarizing the mass educations as the most efficient way to raise workers for the mass manufacturing industry seems more probable. Maybe both :)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;P149 - Proper education is to teach an individual to explore the world in their own creative, individual, independent fashion. Learning how to learn.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;College is very expensive. Infact tuition is getting higher and higher. The result here is that, students are under a lot of debt after the university. Laws are changed so that there is no escape, no bankruptcy. Great technique for indoctrination.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What is the economical reason behind raising the tuition? US is a richer country compared to what it was around 60s when tuition was much more cheap.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;K-12 education and government programs make schools teach children to test. Teachers can't go in independent directions.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;P155 - Teacher making his students do things they don't want to do and leading them to raise their questions while teaching American Revolution.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id="aristocrats-and-democrats"&gt;Aristocrats and Democrats&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bakunin said "A new class of intelligentsia who claims to appropriate all knowledge would move in one of two directions: Red bureaucracy which would make the most oppressive rule ever in the name of the working class or it would recognize that power lies elsewhere, in private capital and become its servants."&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;(P174) About Citizens United vs Federal Election Committee which is about the fact that FEC has legalized corporate bribery of our elected officials: There are two aspects here. Tactical aspect and a principled aspect. On the tactical side this case get people interested in itself and get them thinking so it's good. In principle why would corporations have personal rights? They currently have more rights than people of flesh and blood. They are immortal, protected by state power and they are limited liability. I.e. participants are not personally viable say if a company kills 100k people in Bhopal.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Also they are directed to maximize their shareholder rights at the expense of stakeholder rights by law. Why?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id="pointers-to-read"&gt;Pointers to Read:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Adam Smith&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Edward Bernays&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Manifesto of Joseph Stack&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Holder vs Humanitarian Law Project Case&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Haldor Laxness / Icelandic Nobel laurate /&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A case of exploding Mangoes / Mohammed Hanif&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The great leap forward&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Universal genome&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;http://www.greenpeace.org/usa/en/campaigns/global-warming-and-energy/polluterwatch/The-Lewis-Powell-Memo/&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ron Lieber / Student Debt and a Push For Fairness / New York Times&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Failure by design / Josh Bivens -&amp;gt; Talks about decisions in the last 40 year for US and how it makes sense for the top 10%.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>About Beginnings</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://serdars.github.io/2014/08/14/about-beginnings.html"/>
    <id>https://serdars.github.io/2014/08/14/about-beginnings.html</id>
    <published>2014-08-13T17:52:00-07:00</published>
    <updated>2014-08-16T01:40:58-07:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Serdar Sutay</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Sometimes we make a big deal out of beginnings. We put together detailed plans, prepare ourselves to bravely execute before beginning something. And we expect to feel differently right after them. After all we are not the same person anymore after beginning that thing. The world is a different place now. Or is it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Sometimes we make a big deal out of beginnings. We put together detailed plans, prepare ourselves to bravely execute before beginning something. And we expect to feel differently right after them. After all we are not the same person anymore after beginning that thing. The world is a different place now. Or is it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes we are scared of them. We need to think it through and convince ourselves that it is OK to begin. What if this happens? What if it does not go well? What would other people think of me now that I am doing this? Maybe we are not scared of beginnings but ourselves. Most of the time we don't begin because of this fear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes we trick ourselves into believing that we will begin soon. We research, draft plans, talk to people, write documents… We obsess about them. We imagine ourselves doing it. The pleasure of doing that thing without investing the required effort is sweet, but short lived. We never begin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the reason we make a big deal out of beginnings is rooted in the way we see ourselves. We envision ourselves as unchanging entities and we see beginnings as times when we make a conscious decision to change. How can we make such a change easily without preparing ourselves for it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reality is that we are constantly changing. Beginnings are minor shifts in the constant stream of changes. One needs to stick with them in order to make a major change. I.e. we are not black or white. We are gray with a constantly changing shade. Beginnings are the small shifts that we intentionally make in our shade. And things get a lot easier when we don't make a big deal out of beginnings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="directional-vs-result-based-thinking"&gt;Directional vs Result Based Thinking&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was a TED talk (which I'm not able to find anymore) talking about how our happiness is affected by the way we're trying to achieve our goals. One way is to set a goal, e.g. being a CEO; do anything and everything you can to get to it; and measure yourself based on if you were able to reach that goal or not. Another way is to treat your goal as an aspiration and set yourself smaller goals that progressively gets you closer to it; and measure yourself based on how close you get to your aspiration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Different Paths" class="visual" src="/2014/08/14/about-beginnings/different_paths.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Say you aspire to write a novel; a successful one. The starting poing it Google: "How to write a novel". While you're at it you order the two recommended books and read them. You brainstorm to find an idea worthy of being a novel. You prepare a few character sheets and draft a storyline. Then you worry about miserably failing and go to Google: "How to get published". You start learning about the tricks that makes a novel readable. You start thinking about if these tricks are inline with your philosophy of writing. Then you go back to your draft storyline. You don't like it. Suddenly other things start creeping in your life and you don't have any time to write your novel anymore. Not only you didn't get any closer to your goal, you've also wasted a lot of time. And the worst part is writing a novel still seems to you like a potential goal only reachable if you didn't need to do these other things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="steering"&gt;Steering&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using the second way, you can begin tomorrow by writing a story and having your friends read it. Then you can write a longer story and see the sacrifices required to write a novel. Maybe you can write a short draft and get it to a few people in the publishing industry and see what they think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe you will discover that writing a novel is your over-romanticised dream. Short stories are a better fit for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Moving Path" class="visual" src="/2014/08/14/about-beginnings/moving_goal.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Change the route. Collect the best short stories you have already written. Write a few more and see if this is your true passion. Maybe after writing a few more it gets boring just like the novel You like writing about real things. Change direction again. Write a few articles for internet magazines and send them. See if you would like that. Who knows, maybe you'll discover that drinking better beer is the most important thing in life while covering a Beer Festival. Finally you have an enjoyable passion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now you might ask what if I end up going around and around getting nowhere? You can cross that bridge too when you get there. Don't fall into the trap of getting stuck at the port.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="begin-now"&gt;Begin Now!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many ideas are based on not making a big deal out of beginnings. Lean startup, waterfall vs agile, prototyping instead of writing a document… Planning to start a diet next Monday; start right now by not eating that bag of chips. Planning to start an exercise program, start right now by taking a 15 minutes run. Planning to start spending more time with your family, pick up the phone and call them now!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whatever it is that you are planning to begin; begin tomorrow by taking the first brave step. You will be one step closer to your destination wherever it might be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Says one who has been planning to start a blog for the last few years…&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
