<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Leaf</title>
  <subtitle>One in many, many in one.</subtitle>
  <id>https://serdars.github.io/</id>
  <link href="https://serdars.github.io/"/>
  <link href="https://serdars.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <updated>2015-01-02T11:43:00-08:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Serdar Sutay</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>Peter M. Senge - The Fifth Discipline - Part 6 - Team Learning</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://serdars.github.io/2015/01/02/peter-m-senge-the-fifth-discipline-part-6-team-learning.html"/>
    <id>https://serdars.github.io/2015/01/02/peter-m-senge-the-fifth-discipline-part-6-team-learning.html</id>
    <published>2015-01-02T11:43:00-08:00</published>
    <updated>2015-01-02T14:38:03-08:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Serdar Sutay</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The final discipline in &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peter_Senge"&gt;Peter M. Senge's&lt;/a&gt; framework is the discipline that brings focus to the in-team social dynamics of Personal Mastery, Shared Vision and Mental Models: Team Learning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The final discipline in &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peter_Senge"&gt;Peter M. Senge's&lt;/a&gt; framework is the discipline that brings focus to the in-team social dynamics of Personal Mastery, Shared Vision and Mental Models: Team Learning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When a group of people come together, the IQ (or a metric that measures the capability of the group) can be a lot higher or a lot lower than the total of the IQs of individuals. Best example of highly functioning teams are &lt;strong&gt;Aligned Teams&lt;/strong&gt;. In these teams, in addition to individuals being in the &lt;strong&gt;flow&lt;/strong&gt; state, group as a whole is in &lt;strong&gt;flow&lt;/strong&gt; state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In aligned teams, there is a commonality of purpose, shared vision and an understanding of how to complement one another's efforts. Individuals do not sacrifice personal interests to the larger team. Great jazz musicians know and talk about alignment; having a sense of where music is going and how each is contributing to go towards that direction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Team learning is the discipline of aligning and developing capacity of a team to be able to create the results its members truly desire.&lt;/strong&gt; It is a collaborative discipline. It doesn't make sense to say "I'm practicing team learning". It is based on personal mastery and makes use of shared vision and techniques from mental models. It has three critical dimensions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Being able to think insightfully about complicated situations.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Coordinated innovative action.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Role of the team amongst other teams.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Team learning discipline involves mastering the practices of dialogue and discussion, the two distinct ways of conversation. In order to master these practices, a team must first master how to creatively deal with forces opposing productive dialogue and discussions. Lastly like all other disciplines, practice is required to advance in this discipline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An organization can not become a learning organization unless its teams start treating learning as a discipline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="dialogue-and-discussion"&gt;Dialogue and Discussion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can all recall having conversations with individuals (friends, family members, colleagues, etc…) which had a high impact on the way we see the world. The idea in dialogue is to have a conversation where the participants can reach a view bigger than the total of their views combined. This is a very old idea practiced in ancient Greek and modern day American Indians. Looks like we have lost this ability on the way (probably due to the self centric view promoted by rationalism).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;David Bohm, a leading quantum theorist, asserted that our thought is incoherent and the resulting counter-productiveness is the root cause of all the problems that exist today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Discussion suggests something like a ping - pong, back and forth. Purpose generally is to &lt;strong&gt;win&lt;/strong&gt; and have one's views accepted by the group. You may occasionally accepts other's views to be a part of your own but you want your view to prevail. By contrast dialogue is different. Dia means through and logos means word or meaning. When combined it means "meaning passing through". In dialogue, a group tries to access to the pool of common meaning. In dialogue there is no winning. There is no opposition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PS:&lt;/strong&gt; The idea in dialogue is to have the context that I am not the place where the idea originates from. &lt;a href="http://www.ted.com/talks/elizabeth_gilbert_success_failure_and_the_drive_to_keep_creating?language=en"&gt;Elizabeth Gilbert's TED talk&lt;/a&gt; is a great theory of how we have started seeing ourselves as the source of creativity and can help when practicing dialogue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The purpose of the dialogue is to reveal the incoherence of our own thoughts. There are three types of incoherence:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Thought denies that it is participative.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Thought stops tracking reality and just goes like a program.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Thought establishes its own frame of reference for solving problems which is the root cause of the problems in the first place.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider prejudice. Once a person starts to assume a prototype, prejudice thoughts starts to become an active agent. It participates in the interactions of the person and the prejudiced person. The person can not see how his prejudice shapes what he sees or how he acts. If he can see it, he wouldn't be prejudiced anyways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thought presents itself in front of us and pretends that it does not represent. We are actors that forget they are playing a role. Reality may change but the theater continues. &lt;strong&gt;In dialogue participants become observers of their own thinking to let go of the theater and understand the reality better.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People can generally detect when there is a tension in a conversation. What they do right after that is to take a defensive posture and assume that the reason why the tension is popping up is not because of themselves but because of others or the system. Getting defensive triggers more defensiveness in the other participants and conversation quickly escalates into a discussion without control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If our collective thinking is an ongoing stream, thoughts are leaves floating on the surface. We experience them as thoughts. We misperceive that they are ours because we fail to see the stream of collective thinking from which they arise.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main idea is not some theoretical pure definition of dialogue but develop our skills that will make us recognize our more and more of our incoherences. There are three principle elements of a dialogue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;All participants mus &lt;strong&gt;suspend their assumptions&lt;/strong&gt; and hold them in front of themselves.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;All participants must &lt;strong&gt;regard one another as colleagues&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There must be a &lt;strong&gt;facilitator&lt;/strong&gt; who
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;holds the context&lt;/strong&gt; of the dialogue.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;artfully diminishes the resistance&lt;/strong&gt; to the dialogue.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id="suspending-assumptions"&gt;Suspending Assumptions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea is to realize your assumptions and hold your assumptions to external observation in order to correct them. There is nothing wrong with having assumptions (or thoughts) let them be right or wrong. The problematic part is to hold on to them without being aware of holding on to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This can not be done when you are trying to defend a position. The mind by its nature wants to keep moving away from holding assumptions to adopting non-negotiatable and rigid opinions which we then feel compelled to defend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suspending assumptions is a lot like detecting &lt;strong&gt;Leaps of Abstraction&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;inquirying into the reasoning behind the abstractions&lt;/strong&gt;. In dialogue this suspension should be done collectively. There is a reinforcing process here when more people start to suspend assumptions, the more suitable the environment is for dialogue and the more people start to suspend assumptions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="seeing-each-other-as-colleagues"&gt;Seeing each other as Colleagues&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seeing each other as colleagues is vital to creating a positive tone and vulnerability. Hierarchy is especially problematic to this since people will by definition be in a defensive stance when they see the others as their bosses or decision makers in a conversation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being colleagues doesn't mean sharing the same view. In fact the diversity of views is healthy in dialogue. It is also more easier to carry a dialogue when there are not a diversity of opinions. When there is conflict it is tougher to suspend assumptions and treat each other as colleagues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="facilitator"&gt;Facilitator&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are worried to suspend our assumptions and display them publicly. We have a habitual thinking that these assumptions form our identity and we are really worried about others detecting some errors in our identity. After all we don't want to lose our identity or as we know of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A skilled facilitator has many duties in a dialogue:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ensuring people own the ownership of the process and outcomes. When people start saying "so-and-so won't let us talk about this" or "this is the way it is" facilitator brings the conversation back.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ensures that dialogue doesn't turn into a discussion. Individuals might want to convert the dialogue into discussion without being aware of it.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Is in a fine line being the knowledgable and helpful in the process yet not taking the expert or doctor mantle that would shift the attention away from team members.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But he does this all and influences the flow of development only by participating. For e.g. after someone making an observation the facilitator might way "But the opposite may also be true" to remind of other possibilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The artistry of the dialogue lies in experiencing the flow of meaning and seeing the one thing that needs to be said now.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As teams practice dialogue more and more, the need for a facilitator decreases. Dialogue emerges from leaderless groups once the members have developed the skill and understanding for the need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="balancing-dialogue--discussion"&gt;Balancing Dialogue &amp;amp; Discussion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A team needs both dialogue and discussion in order to effectively function.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dialogue is used when different ideas are presented towards discovering a new view on a situation. Discussion is used when team needs to reach a decision. Before agreements and decisions, discussions are a necessity. Dialogue is divergent where discussions are convergent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An effective team knows when to use dialogue and when to use discussion. A special relationship develops amongst the team members who regularly enter dialogue. They develop a richer understanding of uniqueness of each person's point of view and more they understand how larger understandings emerge from holding one's own point of view gently. &lt;strong&gt;They learn how to hold a position without being hold by their positions.&lt;/strong&gt; Skills used for dialogue help in having a better discussion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="reflection-inquiry--dialogue"&gt;Reflection, Inquiry &amp;amp; Dialogue&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dialogue that is rooted in reflection and inquiry is more reliable and resistant to the special circumstances of the situations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Generally there are two types of consensus. 1-) Focusing down or common denominator 2-) Focusing up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second builds from the fact that we can see a different thing when we look at the reality from someone else's view. This is true for other looking through our view as well. When combined via dialogue, this leads to coming up with a view that is greater than all of our views combined.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conflict-and-defensive-routines"&gt;Conflict and Defensive Routines&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In great teams conflict is productive. In fact, the essence of "visioning" lies in a set of ideas emerging from a set of conflicting ideas. In mediocre teams, conflict represents itself in one of two forms: Either there is an appearance of no conflict in the surface or there is rigid polarization. Managers speak out in polarized teams and no one speaks out in hidden conflict teams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Defensive routines are habits we've acquired over time supported by a set of mental models that we use to protect ourselves form embarrassment and threat that come with exposing our own thinking. &lt;strong&gt;Defensive reasoning protects us from learning the validity of our reasoning.&lt;/strong&gt; Because we are afraid that people will find errors in it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Defensive routines are so diverse and commonplace that we usually do not notice them. "That's a very interesting idea" when we don't have any intention to entertain the idea, deliberately squash an idea in order to avoid having to consider it, etc… Generally the individual in which the defensive routine is operating is not aware of it. In fact if it is not hidden, it wouldn't be operative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deep within the mental models of managers in an organization, is the belief that &lt;strong&gt;managers must know what is going on&lt;/strong&gt;. Those that reach senior positions are masters at appearing to know what is going on and those intent to reach high develop an air of confident knowledge early in their career.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Managers in this state of mind find themselves in one of two binds. 1-) Some internalize the air of confidence and they simply believe that they know the answers to most important problems but to protect their beliefs they must close themselves to alternative views and make themselves un-influenceable. They must be rigid in order to appear confident. 2-) Some believe they are expected to know what is causing the important problems but deep down recognize that they don't. They maintain a facade of confidence to obscure their ignorance. Whichever the bind managers find themselves in, they become highly skillful in defensive routines that preserve the aura as capable decision makers by not revealing the thinking behind their decisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Defensiveness most of the time becomes an accepted part of organizational culture. &lt;strong&gt;We are the carriers of defensive routines and the organizations are the hosts. Once infected, they too become the carriers.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Defensive routines are a response to a problem. The problem is a need to learn arising from a "learning gap". Fundamental solution is inquiry that results eventually in a new understanding and new behavior that is learning. Symptomatic solution is to employ the defensive routine by reducing the "percieved need for learning".&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The more effective defensive routines are, the more effectively they cover up the underlying problems, the less problems are seen and the worse they become. The effective defensive routines are also ••self-sealing**. They obscure their own existence. Thanks to the societal norms, it is not good to expose or even acknowledge that we are being defensive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As in all shifting the burden structures, there are two leverages. 1-) Weaken the symptomatic solution. In this case by weakening the emotional threat one faces for which the defensive routine is employed for. 2-) Strengthening the fundamental solution. In this case by inquiring into the problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But how to make them discussable is a challenge. If you expose another person's defensive routine in a public setting, it for sure is going to backfire. Skillful managers learn to confront defensiveness without producing more defensiveness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They do so by self-disclosure and but inquiring into the causes of their own defensiveness. "I notice that I'm feeling threatened by this new proposal. Can you help me see where this uneasiness is coming from?"&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the presence of a genuinely shared vision, defensive routines become just another aspect of current reality, like the structural conflicts raised during personal mastery. They are in fact useful signals for spotting the times when learning is not happening and especially difficult and important issues. They drain the energy of the team and create a feeling of powerlessness in achieving the vision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is not the absence of defensiveness that characterizes the learning teams, but what happens when the defensiveness is faced. A team that is committed to truth doesn't only talk about what is happening out there but also talks about what is happening in here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="practice"&gt;Practice&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Practice is the missing link to build the discipline of team learning. Great orchestrates, bands, sport teams all practice before the day of play. But for us practicing is really not super practical. Great teams are the ones who stay together for a long time and continuously practice. Creative advertising teams for example stick together most of the time. They even change the companies as a team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beyond the practicing of making a decision, creating the environment and time to step back and reflect on the process of making a decision is necessary in learning. [Slack concept in Kanban]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For future reference, the necessary conditions of a dialogue session are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Having all members of the team together.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Explaining the 3 ground rules (add more as needed)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Enforcing the ground rules so that team acknowledges when someone finds himself not dialoguing but discussing.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Making it possible, indeed encouraging, for team members to raise the most difficult, subtle and conflictual issues essential to team's work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id="team-learning-and-the-fifth-discipline"&gt;Team Learning and The Fifth Discipline&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Systems Thinking most importantly helps practicing team learning. The first help of it is because it helps us to view the conflicts in a whole way without excluding ourselves from them which helps for us to suspend our assumptions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest help of it all is by giving as a language to talk about our problems. There are many benefits of having a language to talk about complexity and defensive routines:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Helps us reach to a common understanding of complexity.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Helps us dedicate time to talking about complexity.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Visualize our emotions and helps us able to resolve emotional conflicts more easily.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Help us get to a common understanding by inquiring into our thinking.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Create a friendly environment by making it easy to talk about defensive routines.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Peter M. Senge - The Fifth Discipline - Part 5 - Shared Vision</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://serdars.github.io/2014/12/30/peter-m-senge-the-fifth-discipline-part-5-shared-vision.html"/>
    <id>https://serdars.github.io/2014/12/30/peter-m-senge-the-fifth-discipline-part-5-shared-vision.html</id>
    <published>2014-12-30T09:51:00-08:00</published>
    <updated>2014-12-30T12:24:34-08:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Serdar Sutay</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The best example of Shared Vision is when Marcus Crassus gives the slaves the chance to save their lives if they give away Spartacus. Each and every one of the slaves respond with "I'm the Spartacus" since they are loyal to the shared vision of freedom Spartacus has inspired in them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The best example of Shared Vision is when Marcus Crassus gives the slaves the chance to save their lives if they give away Spartacus. Each and every one of the slaves respond with "I'm the Spartacus" since they are loyal to the shared vision of freedom Spartacus has inspired in them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shared Vision is at its simplest form the answer to the question "What do we want to create?". Just as everyone carries their personal vision as pictures for themselves, shared vision is the picture each member of a group carries in their minds for their group. It is formed when members of a group have similar pictures in their minds and when they are committed to having that picture not just for themselves but together. They derive power from their deep caring for the vision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="why-shared-vision-matters"&gt;Why Shared Vision matters?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;None of the big accomplishments in the history was possible without a shared vision amongst a group of people. This triggered a big push in corporate leadership to come up with a "vision" for their companies. But many of the vision statements produced are nothing more than just words. They are mostly extrinsic. They focus on achieving something relative to an outsider, like beating a competitor or achieving highest market share. When a vision is only extrinsic, it can't create genuine excitement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An intrinsic shared vision uplifts people's aspirations. They become part of a larger purpose, which subconsciously every person desires. Organization is no longer "their company". It becomes "our company". It incites courage in individuals and moves them past &lt;strong&gt;compliance&lt;/strong&gt; into &lt;strong&gt;commitment&lt;/strong&gt;. It fosters risk taking and experimentation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most importantly it incites &lt;strong&gt;long term focus&lt;/strong&gt;. For years organizations and individuals theorized how to keep long term focus rather than giving into short term gains. &lt;strong&gt;It is simply not possible to convince human being rationally to take a long term view.&lt;/strong&gt; People do not focus on the long term when they have to. They only focus on it when they want to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shared Vision extends the principles of personal mastery into the world of collective aspirations and shared commitment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="how-to-create-a-shared-vision"&gt;How to create a Shared Vision?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Shared Visions emerge from personal visions.&lt;/strong&gt; A group's shared vision can not be solely the personal vision of its founder. It can start there but one can't apply his personal vision to the group. Many leaders forget this and mix their personal vision and the shared vision of their group. The result in this case is &lt;strong&gt;compliance&lt;/strong&gt; not &lt;strong&gt;commitment&lt;/strong&gt;. In order to develop a shared vision, personal mastery is a requirement. Each member's personal vision provides the bedrock for the shared vision. The art of visionary leadership is building a shared vision from personal visions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Shared Vision is not a photograph but a hologram.&lt;/strong&gt; When you cut a photograph into pieces, each piece shows only part of the whole image. But for a hologram even the smallest piece captures the whole image intact. In each piece the whole image is represented even though slightly differently. When you add all the pieces you get the whole image but more intense and more lifelike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first step to create a shared vision is to let go the traditional vision concept that comes down from up high in an organization. These efforts are most of the time a single effort to describe and overarching strategical direction to the company, they do not come alive. Second problem with these efforts is the fact that they are not build on individual's personal visions. Finally vision is not a solution to a problem. It is the central daily work of leaders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not to say that shared vision can not come from up high. They most of the time do. But some level of "bubbling up" from down below is always part of the process. Leadership must be careful not to assume that their personal visions become organization's vision when they assume a position of leadership. They mistakenly word "my vision" as "our vision". They should remember Mark Twain's suggestion that &lt;strong&gt;The use of word "we" should be reserved for kings and people with tapeworm.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="spreading-vision---commitment-vs-compliance"&gt;Spreading Vision - Commitment vs Compliance&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spreading of vision is not about giving inspiring speeches and inspiring the troops. It is about solving the daily problems with the vision in mind. The process is same whether the vision originates in the middle or at the top.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today it is very common to hear managers talking about "getting buy in" or "selling" around the vision. Yet there is a world of difference between &lt;strong&gt;selling&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;enrolling&lt;/strong&gt;. Selling means getting someone to do something that he might not do if he were in full possession of all facts. Enrolling, by contrast, literally means placing one's name on the roll.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enrollment is the process of becoming part of something by choice. You are committed when you enroll. People enroll in social causes out of genuine desire and once a year they make a donation. But when they are committed the cause can count on them. They will do whatever it takes to make the vision real. In today's organizations, relatively low number of people are enrolled and even fewer are committed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Great majority are in a state of compliance. There are multiple levels of compliance which makes it difficult to differentiate enrollment and commitment from compliance:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Commitment&lt;/strong&gt;: Wants it. Will make it happen. Creates any "laws" that are needed.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Enrollment&lt;/strong&gt;: Wants it. Will do whatever can be done within the "spirit of the law".&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Genuine Compliance&lt;/strong&gt;: Sees the benefit of the vision. Does everything expected and more. Follows the "letter of the law". "Good soldier"&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Formal Compliance&lt;/strong&gt;: On the whole sees the benefit of the vision. Does what is expected and no more. "Pretty good soldier"&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Grudging Compliance&lt;/strong&gt;: Does not see the benefit of the vision. Also doesn't want to lose the job. Does enough of what's expected because he has to but also lets it be known that he is not really on board.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Noncompliance&lt;/strong&gt;: Does not see the benefit of the vision and will not do what is expected. "I won't do it, you can't make me".&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Apathy&lt;/strong&gt;: Neither for nor against the vision. No interest. No energy. "Is it five o'clock yet?"&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Great way to think about it is using the speed limits. Genuinely compliant will never drive over the speed limit. Formally compliant will drive 5 - 7 miles over the speed limit because you will not get a ticket in most states when you do so. Grudgingly compliant will drive the same speed and continuously complain about it. Noncompliant driver will not care about the limit and do everything possible to avoid troopers. Committed person would drive that speed even if it was not the legal limit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In most organizations formal and genuine compliance go "along with the program". Noncompliance or grudging compliance usually stands out since they let their opposition be known. Most problematic case is genuine compliance often mistaken for enrollment or commitment. They will do what is expected of them willingly. They also think they are committed. And they are but only to "being part of the team". These people also caress the egos of leaders if they are into it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Couple things that should be noted is that, some people have been never asked to commit to anything for themselves. They should be approached with gentleness. Also commitment should be gentle not to infringe the independence of the individual. After all individuals should first be committed to a personal vision, second to the shared vision which emancipates from the personal vision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="guidelines-for-enrollment--commitment"&gt;Guidelines for Enrollment &amp;amp; Commitment&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to incite enrollment:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Be enrolled yourself. Don't sell to get to superficial agreement since it sows the seeds for future resentment.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Be on the level. Do not inflate benefits or sweep problems under the rug.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Let the other person choose. Have a willingness for making the individual free to choose.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many times when we need compliance. In these situations it is better to be open about it. "I know you do not wholeheartedly agree but decision is made and we need your support in getting through this".&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="anchoring-vision-in-governing-ideas"&gt;Anchoring Vision in Governing Ideas&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Building a shared vision is one part of the activity of building the governing ideas for an enterprise: vision, purpose or mission and core values.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Vision: What? The picture we seek to create.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Purpose or Mission: Why? Why do we exist?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Core Values: How? How do we want to act? How do we want life to be on a day-to-day basis?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taken together, they answer the question "What do we believe in?". People have a genuine need to be part of an ennobling mission or purpose. But it is abstract. Vision makes the purpose more concrete as a guiding star.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that "What do we want to create?" is different than "What do we want to avoid?". Negative visions are more common in today's organizations but they are limiting for 3 reasons:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Energy for building something is directed to preventing something else.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They carry a subtle message of powerlessness. We only pull together against a threat.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They are inevitably short term. They are not applicable once the thread disappears.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The power of human beings is to organize against a generative purpose instead of a reactive purpose such as threat to survival.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similar to personal mastery, effectiveness of an organization is based on how they &lt;strong&gt;hold&lt;/strong&gt; the creative tension, i.e. their vision while remaining committed to current reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="shared-vision-and-systems-thinking"&gt;Shared Vision and Systems Thinking&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shared Vision operates in a reinforcing process of "people talking about the vision and pursuing the vision", "clarity of shared vision" and "enthusiasm toward vision". But there are many limiting processes that can derail this cycle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Inability to inquire and harmonize opinion diversity:&lt;/strong&gt; "people talking about the vision and pursuing the vision" eventually leads to "diversity of views", "conflicting visions" and "polarization" which decreases the "clarity of shared vision". The limiting factor in this process is lacking the ability to inquire and harmonize different opinions hence the leverage. Do people feel that the vision is set in stone? Must those who doesn't agree with the vision change their views? Do people feel their own visions do not matter? If answer to any of these questions is yes, this process is active. Hologram aspect of shared visions should be protected. The most effective way to do this is to utilize the inquiry skills used to surface out our mental models.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Capacity to hold Creative Tension&lt;/strong&gt;: Visions also die because of the apparent difficulty in bringing the vision into reality. "clarity of shared vision" leads to "perceived gap between vision and current reality", "discouragement" (emotional tension) and decreases the "enthusiasm toward vision". This is why personal mastery and the ability to hold creative tension is the bedrock to develop a shared vision.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Time required for current reality&lt;/strong&gt;: This process is a limiting factor which results from "people talking about the vision and pursuing the vision" to "time required for developing vision", "time available for vision", "focus on vision" and "decrease in clarity of shared vision". Leverage is in finding ways to focus less time and effort on ongoing crises and managing the current reality.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Time pressure or ability to inquire into vision&lt;/strong&gt;: When people start talking about vision, they start proselytizing (religiously converting each other) in order to settle down and have clarity on the vision. "enthusiasm toward vision" leads to "proselytizing", "decrease in quality of relationships" and decrease in "enthusiasm toward vision". The leverage in this process is to keep individual's relationship to vision either with time or skills. In order to keep our fragile relationship we need to respect one another otherwise we will get separated into insider (true believers) and outsiders of the vision.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Systems Thinking brings the missing synergy when talking about the vision. It gives us the framework not to feel powerlessness against the external factor. It provides people a language to speak about otherwise unspoken interrelationships and keep the optimism and the generative drive towards clarifying and reaching our vision step by step.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Peter M. Senge - The Fifth Discipline - Part 4 - Mental Models</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://serdars.github.io/2014/12/30/peter-m-senge-the-fifth-discipline-part-4-mental-models.html"/>
    <id>https://serdars.github.io/2014/12/30/peter-m-senge-the-fifth-discipline-part-4-mental-models.html</id>
    <published>2014-12-29T19:48:00-08:00</published>
    <updated>2014-12-30T09:53:58-08:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Serdar Sutay</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Notes and commentary on &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peter_Senge"&gt;Peter M. Senge's&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/The-Fifth-Discipline-Practice-Organization/dp/0553456342"&gt;The Fifth Discipline&lt;/a&gt; continues with third building block: Mental Models.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Notes and commentary on &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peter_Senge"&gt;Peter M. Senge's&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/The-Fifth-Discipline-Practice-Organization/dp/0553456342"&gt;The Fifth Discipline&lt;/a&gt; continues with third building block: Mental Models.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="mental-models"&gt;Mental Models&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the great ideas &amp;amp; novel ways of doing things fail when they face with reality. This is because we have a deeply embedded understanding of how things work and we subconsciously discard any idea conflicting with them even tough there is no good rational reason against these ideas. This is why being mindful about our mental models is fundamental to learning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;None of us can carry an organization in our minds, or a family or a project. We carry images and assumptions around things. We carry mental models. They can be simple generalizations such as "People are not trustworthy" or they can be complex theories about why the people interact with each other as they do. If we believe that our friend lacks self-confidence, we have the tendency to see this in our friend's behavior and continually intervene with this belief.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason they are so powerful is because they affect what we see. Two people with different mental models walking into a party sees different things. As Einstein reminded us, &lt;strong&gt;"Our theories determine what we measure".&lt;/strong&gt; When executives from US car manufacturers went into Japan to understand why they were losing market share, they came back with the belief that they were not shown the real manufacturing plants because there was no inventory on site. Their mental models prevented them to see the fact that Japanese were operating with a different system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The problem with the mental models doesn't lie in the fact that they are right or wrong - by definition all models are simplifications.&lt;/strong&gt; The problem is that, they operate in our subconscious. When they are wrong and unexamined, the gap between them and the reality widens overtime resulting in increasingly counter-productive actions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They are especially problematic in organizations. When multiple people share a mental model, it is harder to change because it is not enough if one person detects it and changes his thinking. Another complicating factor is that people has a habit to display different behavior without changing their beliefs. This habit is installed by old school hierarchical leadership. There are countless examples of adopting a new idea and seeing benefit of it but not sticking with it overtime because of the embedded mental models.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="changing-mental-models-in-organizations"&gt;Changing Mental Models in Organizations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Book contains an example of how Shell and BP has changed their understanding of the world and their approach to business by changing their mental models. One of them embedded the practice into strategic planning by games with the aim to influence the mental images of decision makers and the other distributed the decision making and business accountability to local divisions by developing networks. There are countless number of ways to surface mental models. The correct way depends on the nature of the organization, but it is not writing a document.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Promoting personal awareness and reflective skills and providing infrastructure for regular practice is the common element. Saying "We value openness" doesn't mean people are promoting openness. Everyone talks about creating a culture and improving a culture. But practice goes beyond the words (and also takes time).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the people in the world are far far away from being able to have open &amp;amp; productive discussions with each other. This is a normality. Thankfully there are tools to practice in order to makes this job easier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Theory and method for examining the reasoning in our actions is called &lt;strong&gt;action science&lt;/strong&gt;. There are many tools developed by its practitioners. The most common and effective one is &lt;strong&gt;Reflection in Action&lt;/strong&gt; which involves recalling a conflict, recalling what was said as well as what were we thinking at that moment of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are more than one way of looking at complex issues. For e.g. eastern and western approach to management. None of them are wrong and the fact of right and wrong does not matter. Understanding the fact that what we subconsciously see as &lt;strong&gt;truths&lt;/strong&gt; are just &lt;strong&gt;assumptions&lt;/strong&gt; makes us analyze them and decrease the gap between them and reality when needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="tools-and-skills"&gt;Tools and Skills&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two broad categories of skills core to the discipline of mental models are: &lt;strong&gt;Reflective&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Inquiry&lt;/strong&gt; skills. Where we want to get to in this discipline is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Facing up to distinctions between &lt;strong&gt;Espoused Theories vs Theories-In-Use&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Recognizing &lt;strong&gt;Leaps of Abstraction&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Exposing the &lt;strong&gt;Left Hand Column&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Balancing Inquiry &amp;amp; Advocacy&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id="reflective-practice"&gt;Reflective Practice&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to become &lt;strong&gt;generative&lt;/strong&gt; learners, life long learners at one point need to become &lt;strong&gt;reflective practitioners&lt;/strong&gt; to overcome their own shortcomings. They constantly reflect on themselves to surface their mental models and put them under scrutiny. When good musicians improvise together, they constantly check themselves and their group to understand where they are going individually and going as a group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="espoused-theory-vs-theory-in-use"&gt;Espoused Theory vs Theory-In-Use&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we face our mental models and realize the differences between them and the current reality, we might face discouragement, hypocrisy even cynicism. This is due to our habitual understanding of failure. When we realize the difference and acknowledge it we have a chance to learn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first question to pose is "Do I really value the espoused theory?" or "Is it really part of my vision?". If there is no commitment to the espoused theory, then the gap is not between my vision and reality (no tension) but it is between reality and a view I advance (maybe because of how it will make me look to others).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;An ruthlessly compassionate partner&lt;/strong&gt; is our best friend to surface our mental models and put them under scrutiny. As the old saying goes &lt;strong&gt;The eye can not see the eye.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="leaps-of-abstraction"&gt;Leaps of Abstraction&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When our minds are flying at the speed of light in a busy day we constantly make &lt;strong&gt;leaps of abstraction&lt;/strong&gt; such as "Laura doesn't care about people". They happen when we move from direct observation to generalization without testing. It is important to be able to detect these since they might not be correct. But we shouldn't be doing this detection constantly because it will overheat our brains. When we look into the observation with compassion we can understand the causes and see if our leap is correct.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These leaps are not always around the common real life happenings. Another example is "Customers buy our product based on price, quality of customer service is not a factor". These are especially hard to detect and more dangerous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The steps to detect leaps of abstraction:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What is my belief about the way world works?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What is the 'data' on with this belief is based?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Am I willing to consider this generalization may be inaccurate or misleading?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;(If the answer is no, there is no point in proceeding)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;TODO: Separate the belief from data and test directly when possible.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id="left-hand-column"&gt;Left-Hand Column&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a technique to see how our mental models operate in particular situations. It is about capturing the behind the scenes thoughts that occur during a conversation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;
What I'm Thinking     What is Said
-----------------     ------------
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="balancing-inquiry--advocacy"&gt;Balancing Inquiry &amp;amp; Advocacy&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most managers are trained to be advocates. But when we encounter issues that are more complex and diverse from our personal experience we need to tap into insights from other people. This is done by inquiry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When two advocates face each other, they usually advocate their own views even when they have the best intentions to have an open candid conversation. As they reasonable and calmly argue for their points, their positions become more and more rigid. In fact there is a systems archetype for this situation: &lt;strong&gt;Escalation&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The leverage to break the Escalation loop is to ask inquiry questions. But pure inquiry is also limited. We almost always have a view regardless of the fact that whether we believe or not this it is correct. Pure inquiry blocks learning by hiding our view behind infinite number of questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The right move is to combine inquiry and advocacy, &lt;strong&gt;reciprocal inquiry&lt;/strong&gt;. In this mode the goal is not to win the argument but to find the best argument. The simple change in the communication is to word one's view as "Here is my view and here is how I arrived at it. What do you think?" Putting things into checklist form:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Make your reasoning explicit.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Encourage others to explore your view.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Encourage others to provide different views.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Inquire into other's views.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;State your assumptions about the other's views if any.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;State the data on which the assumptions are based.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Don't inquire if you are not genuinely interested in other's response.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When at impasse:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Ask what data or logic can change the other's view.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Ask if we can create an experiment together that might provide more information.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Ask what might be making talking openly about this subject difficult.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id="does-agreement-matter"&gt;Does agreement matter?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the time, mental models around a complicated situation might not agree. And this is OK. The important bit is to surface the mental models and put them under scrutiny in a safe environment. Agreement might not surface. But if the parties are all committed to truth, they will still progress decreasing the gap between mental models and current reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="mental-models-and-fifth-discipline"&gt;Mental Models and Fifth Discipline&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without surfacing the gap between our automatical mental models and the reality, progressing towards our personal vision will be slower if not blocked. Creating an environment where doing so is safe will provide the practice infrastructure to break hierarchical decision making and increase the autonomy and involvement of the participants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can detect progress when people stop talking like "Things are this way" and start talking like "The way I see it, things are this way".&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Carmine Gallo - Talk Like TED</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://serdars.github.io/2014/12/29/carmine-gallo-talk-like-ted.html"/>
    <id>https://serdars.github.io/2014/12/29/carmine-gallo-talk-like-ted.html</id>
    <published>2014-12-29T11:22:00-08:00</published>
    <updated>2014-12-29T11:50:14-08:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Serdar Sutay</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/Talk-Like-TED-Public-Speaking-Secrets/dp/1250041120"&gt;Talk Like TED&lt;/a&gt; a book from &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carmine_Gallo"&gt;Carmine Gallo&lt;/a&gt; has a lot of summarization of TED talks for an easy read. But it also has great pointers on preparing a great talk. Here are my raw notes out of this book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/Talk-Like-TED-Public-Speaking-Secrets/dp/1250041120"&gt;Talk Like TED&lt;/a&gt; a book from &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carmine_Gallo"&gt;Carmine Gallo&lt;/a&gt; has a lot of summarization of TED talks for an easy read. But it also has great pointers on preparing a great talk. Here are my raw notes out of this book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are three foundations of great talks: EMOTIONAL, NOVEL &amp;amp; MEMORABLE.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aristotle named 3 elements to a persuasive talk in &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Modes_of_persuasion"&gt;On Rhetoric&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ethos: Perceived authority of the presenter.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pathos: Appealing to emotions.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Logos: Logic, data supporting the point.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id="emotional"&gt;EMOTIONAL&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Unleash the Master within
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;What is the meaningful connection between you, yourself, and your story?&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;What are you passionate about?&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;What makes your heart sing?&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;What is your Personal Vision?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Master the Art of Storytelling
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Stories need to reach heart and mind.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Connect at emotional level before getting started.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Types of stories one can include in a presentation:
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Personal: Most effective. Display of vulnerability. No ego included.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Stories of Others: Similar without the personal connection.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Brands / Corporations / …: Same form of identity.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Avoid buzzwords &amp;amp; cliches
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Develop a list of words to avoid.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Use heroes &amp;amp; villains&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Any persons life when told in a humble, rich and non-egotic way is a great story.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Have a Conversation
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Practice, practice &amp;amp; practice.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Deliver it as if you are having a natural conversation.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Get help with planning.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Early feedback (record yourself and watch it if no other feedback type exists)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Develop your presentation from whole to pieces.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Conversational Tone:
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Find your optimum combination of: Rate / Volume / Pitch / Pause&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Great leaders and communicators have an air of confidence (ethos)&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Using gestures frees up some mental capabilities for the listeners.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Use gestures in key moments.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Keep gestures in the power sphere: Eye level plus and minus amr length.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Easy fixes:
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Standing rigidly: Walk around the room.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Fidgeting / Tapping: Move with a purpose.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id="novel"&gt;NOVEL&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Teach me something new
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Human brain loves to learn new things.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Make ire relevant and easy to understand.
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Link it to daily life.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Aim to leave with "Hey I learnt something" feeling.
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;(It is also a thing to watch out for since this feeling can trick one into thinking they are an expert on a topic)&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Have a twitter friendly headline.
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;What is the one thing people need to know?&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Deliver Jaw-Dropping Moments
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Bill Gates releasing mosquitos.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;They create "emotionally charged event" which brains can remember more easily.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Unexpected / shocking statistics.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Creative Messaging (iPhone announcement made subtly with an iPad, a phone and an internet device…)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Image &amp;amp; Video&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Memorable Headlines&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Always end in a high note.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lighten Up
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Brain loves humor.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;How to be funny without being funny?
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Anecdotes, observation &amp;amp; personal stories&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Analogies, metaphors, quotes&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Videos, photos&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id="memorable"&gt;MEMORABLE&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;18 minute rule
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Anything longer should be broken down into a soft break every 10 minutes.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Don't let the cognitive backlog grow.
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Listening is draining.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Human mind can understate / store 3 pieces of information at the same time.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Human mind can "keep in mind" 7 plus &amp;amp; minus 2 things.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Step by Step:
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Twitter friendly headline&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;3 key messages&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;3 supporting stories, statistics&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Paint a mental picture with multisensory experiences
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Deliver presentations that touch: sight, sound, taste, smell, touch.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;When possible show a picture rather than words.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;When possible show the thing rather than its picture (demo)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stay in your lane
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Be authentic, open, transparent.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Spotting phonies are easy (System 2 does this constantly).&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Trying to be something other than you are, and you will lose the confidence and trust (ethos) of the audience really fast.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Personal Mastery Poster</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://serdars.github.io/2014/12/29/personal-mastery-poster.html"/>
    <id>https://serdars.github.io/2014/12/29/personal-mastery-poster.html</id>
    <published>2014-12-29T11:03:00-08:00</published>
    <updated>2014-12-30T09:53:54-08:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Serdar Sutay</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Personal Mastery concept from &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peter_Senge"&gt;Peter M. Senge&lt;/a&gt; is a thing that we need to constantly keep in the back of our minds. Here is a poster that we can keep in our eye sight to remind us this concept.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Personal Mastery concept from &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peter_Senge"&gt;Peter M. Senge&lt;/a&gt; is a thing that we need to constantly keep in the back of our minds. Here is a poster that we can keep in our eye sight to remind us this concept.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img title="Personal Mastery Poster" class="full-width" src="/images/posters/personal-mastery.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can bookmark this poster in this address:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://serdars.github.io/images/posters/personal-mastery.png"&gt;https://serdars.github.io/images/posters/personal-mastery.png&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Peter M. Senge - The Fifth Discipline - Part 3 - Personal Mastery</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://serdars.github.io/2014/12/19/peter-m-senge-the-fifth-discipline-part-3-personal-mastery.html"/>
    <id>https://serdars.github.io/2014/12/19/peter-m-senge-the-fifth-discipline-part-3-personal-mastery.html</id>
    <published>2014-12-18T19:29:00-08:00</published>
    <updated>2014-12-30T09:53:47-08:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Serdar Sutay</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;One of the most important topics in &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peter_Senge"&gt;Peter M. Senge's&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/The-Fifth-Discipline-Practice-Organization/dp/0553456342"&gt;The Fifth Discipline&lt;/a&gt;: Personal Mastery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;One of the most important topics in &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peter_Senge"&gt;Peter M. Senge's&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/The-Fifth-Discipline-Practice-Organization/dp/0553456342"&gt;The Fifth Discipline&lt;/a&gt;: Personal Mastery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personal Mastery is the discipline of personal growth and learning. It is a generative activity. It covers the acquisition and development of competencies and skills but goes beyond it. It requires spiritual unfolding but it is more than that. At its core, it is composed of doing only two things:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Continuously clarifying what is important to us&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Clearly seeing current reality as it is&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sadly "mastery" word has bad connotations associated with it. In this context it doesn't suggest dominance over other things in life. A great example is John Petrucci. He is a great master but he doesn't dominate guitar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to continually clarify what is important to us, our personal vision, we need to learn more and more about ourselves. In order to learn more about ourselves we need to learn to be able to see the reality clearly. The clear we see the reality, we clear we can define what is really important for us. This is a reinforcing process based on learning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Learning in this sense doesn't mean acquiring more information. It is incorporating any information we acquire in our lives in order to expand our ability to produce results we would like to achieve. It is a never ending life long process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a person with high level of personal mastery:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Personal Vision is a calling rather than simply a good idea.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They see the current reality as an ally, not an enemy.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They work with the existing forces rather than resist them.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They feel part of a larger creative process that they can influence but can not unilaterally control.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why do we want personal mastery? As an organization, if the people working in the organization are committed to continuously improving themselves, this is in the interest of the organization. The happy people produce happy projects. As an individual we want it because we want it. Who doesn't want to achieve the thing they want most in life?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Organizations however sometimes resist personal mastery. Main reason is that, it is not easily quantifiable also sometimes due to cynicism. In order to fight cynicism, one needs to undestand the source of it. Most of the times it is due to a trauma one experienced. And lastly resistance comes from fear which is the primary blocker of learning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Approaching personal vision as a means to organization's goal devalues the relationship between the individual and the organization. Goal should be to create covenantal relationships rather than contractuals ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="personal-vision"&gt;Personal Vision&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personal Vision comes from within. Most of the times we have goals and objectives but no real vision. Most of the time goals point to things that we want to get rid of (aversion) in our lives. Let's use &lt;strong&gt;negative vision&lt;/strong&gt; as a term for these tendencies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another subtler form to watch out for is "focusing on the means not the result". This generally creates &lt;strong&gt;diminished vision&lt;/strong&gt;. Part of our vision is high market share. But why? In order to be more profitable. But why?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;The ability to focus on ultimate intrinsic desires, not only secondary goals, is a cornerstone of personal mastery.&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The vision can not be talked about without a purpose in life. Regardless of the ontological answer to this question, life's purpose is a useful concept to use. Purpose is similar to a direction, a general heading. Vision is a specific destination. Purpose is abstract. Vision is concrete. Vision without an underlying purpose is just a good idea. Purpose without a vision has no sense of appropriate scale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately vision is intrinsic, not relative. It is desired for its intrinsic value. It is multi-dimensional. There is material aspects, how much money we want to have; service facets, helping others; etc… All are part of what we truly want.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to develop a personal vision, one needs to approach it as a discipline and clear it constantly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a person with high level of personal mastery:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Is courageous enough to take a stand for his vision.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id="creative-tension"&gt;Creative Tension&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The gap between the current reality and the vision creates tension. Because we would like to resolve this gap. Not being able to resolve it quickly leads to two potential cases. If we're holding onto our vision strong enough it creates energy, a.k.a. creative tension, to pull us forward. If not, it creates emotional tension that pulls us back. Pretty much all the times we experience both.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We should be mindful when holding the creative tension. It can be reduced in two ways. 1-) lowering the vision. 2-) Getting closer to the vision. 2 is always harder than 1. We &lt;strong&gt;shift the burden&lt;/strong&gt; by symptomatic solutions in order to reduce the emotional tension (not thinking about our vision or lowering the vision).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="failure"&gt;Failure&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is not about what the vision is, it is more about what the vision does. E.g. Head of Xerox R &amp;amp; D had the vision to revolutionize the education system by having devices for students and teachers. But he ended up creating PC. Did he fail? NBA player who was the MVP 12 / 13 times in his team used to watch himself after every match and rate his play. His maximum score in his career was 65. Did he fail?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Failure is an evidence of gap between current reality and vision. Opportunity for learning. They are not about unworthiness or powerlessness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mastery of Creative Tension, builds patience and perseverance. This changes the approach to failures. The more clear picture of the current reality we can get to, the more clearly we can understand how we can reach our vision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="structural-conflict"&gt;Structural Conflict&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Structural Conflicts are byproducts of our emotional tension due to the gap between current reality and vision. The most two common underlying emotions that it triggers are powerlessness and unworthiness for the vision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We employ 3 habitual strategies to address structural conflicts:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Erode the vision.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Conflict manipulation: Avoiding, negative vision, …&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Willpower: Pushing our way through the conflict. Has very small leverage.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Author faces a situation where the people continuously let him down during the critical time in the projects. He willpowers his way through the project with the mental model that people always let other people down. Once the conflict is recognized he can develop coping strategies by setting better goals, reducing the pressure on people etc… We should be aware that we can't make the choice to change unless we are aware of our current reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pretty much all of us develop these responses through our development and experiences. In order to change these habitual responses, we need to change our sub-conscious beliefs that we are unworthy of our vision or powerless to achieve that vision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So where is the leverage?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="commitment-to-the-truth"&gt;Commitment to the Truth&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The way to change any underlying belief is being committed to the truth. (Same idea that meditators reached and explained a little further long time ago)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commitment to the Truth, doesn't mean seeking the absolute final word or ultimate cause. It is the relentless effort to understand structures underlying the events in the world and in ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A person with high level of personal mastery:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;See more of the structural conflicts underlying their own behavior.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id="using-the-subconscious"&gt;Using the Subconscious&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Subconscious is continuously learning. By focusing on the interaction between conscious and subconscious we can improve our learning (Now welcome to Daniel Kahneman's ideas). As we deepen our rapport between conscious and subconscious, we can teach it more complex tasks like detecting certain structural conflicts which in the end improves personal mastery further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Focusing on the desired result&lt;/strong&gt; for example is a skill. Once we learn this skill and once we pick an intrinsic personal vision, our subconscious keep our focus on our vision continuously. We focus and perform better when we truly care about the desired outcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="practicing-personal-mastery"&gt;Practicing Personal Mastery&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Practicing Personal Mastery creates more than trivial results in individuals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Sufi story talks about a blind man and a crippled man getting out of a forest by blind man carrying the crippled man and crippled man telling where to go. Crippled man represents the intuition and the blind man represents reason. We will find our way out when two are integrated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Practicing personal mastery doesn't aim to integrate the reason and intuition but they achieve it naturally. The integration is not one or the other at a time. Systems thinking helps with the integration by providing the language to folks to explain intuitions with reason.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="connectedness"&gt;Connectedness&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we understand the explanations of intuitions, we see that we do not exist in a different place than the external world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The story of the baby who happens to hold on to his ear and experiences discomfort without being aware of the fact that he himself is causing the discomfort. He pulls harder to get rid of the discomfort only to make things worse. When he discovers that he doesn't do it again. But as he grows up he starts taking a lot of the things in the world as given and ends up as all of us losing the connection between our actions and the external world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="compassion"&gt;Compassion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we discover our connectedness and more and more structural processes; compassion is automatic. We begin to see all of use are trapped in structures, structures that are both embedded in our thinking and in our interpersonal social lives. Once we see that we are part of systems that dictate our behavior, compassion comes up by its own rather than feelings of anger and blame.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="commitment-to-the-whole"&gt;Commitment to the Whole&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And with compassion, we are automatically drawn to the whole. We don't see self motivated goals worthy of being our visions anymore. Our personal visions automatically become more intrinsic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="fostering-personal-mastery"&gt;Fostering Personal Mastery&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want people not to develop their personal mastery, just force them. For sure it will backfire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fostering it requires setting up a right environment for people to be able to develop their skills and being a role model.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
